<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Typed Out</title>
    <link href="https://bje.id.au/blog/atom.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://bje.id.au/blog" />
    <id>https://bje.id.au/blog/atom.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name>Byron Ellacott</name>
        <email></email>
    </author>
    <updated>2020-11-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <entry>
    <title>Programming the TRS-20's FPGA</title>
    <link href="https://bje.id.au/blog/posts/trs20/018-fpga-programming.html" />
    <id>https://bje.id.au/blog/posts/trs20/018-fpga-programming.html</id>
    <published>2020-11-21T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-11-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are many things on the virtual TODO list for the TRS-20. But topping them out has to be the final task required to have the board become self-sufficient: making the FPGA capable of burning itself a new bitstream to its SPI Flash ROM.</p>
<p>As I mentioned in my last post, I’m not in this project to do absolutely everything for myself. Where there’s existing code, I’ll happily use it - unless I think I’ve got something to learn or fun to have. This bit of work is both learning and fun (or perhaps <a href="https://www.theoryoffun.com/">both</a>) so I’m going to author my own SPI master in Verilog. But that’s not what this post is about.</p>
<p>Instead, this post talks about the process of building, testing, and understanding Verilog code, from the perspective of a novice to the field.</p>
<!--more-->
<h1 id="getting-started-with-an-fpga">Getting started with an FPGA</h1>
<p>My FPGA is an iCE40HX1K. I chose this particular part for a few reasons. Crucially, it’s available in a TQFP-100 package, which is right at the very extreme edge of my ability to solder. It’s large enough to do interesting things with, supports 3.3V I/O, and can be clocked at speeds much higher than I’m likely to try to clock it. And just as importantly as being able to solder it to a PCB, it is supported by an open source toolchain that I can fit into my usual sort of workflows.</p>
<p>An FPGA is <a href="http://blog.notdot.net/2012/10/Build-your-own-FPGA">more or less</a> a grid of cells, with each cell consisting of a look-up table (LUT) and a D flip-flop (DFF) and routing to connect the cells to each other and to the I/O pins. Almost every aspect of this is controlled by SRAM inside the IC, which in turn is programmed using a bitstream loaded from the SPI Flash.</p>
<p>FPGAs are also known for having pretty horrendously bad vendor software. This is especially true if you’re a Mac user, since no-one seems to support Macs natively. The downloads are huge (if there’s even free tools in the first place) and they’re not always compatible with using git to manage changes. I tried to persevere with Quartus for Altera CPLDs and entry-level FPGAs for a little while, but it just wasn’t a good experience.</p>
<p>Enter <a href="http://bygone.clairexen.net/icestorm/">Project Icestorm</a>. This is a project that documented the bitstream format of the iCE40 family of FPGAs, and created tools to synthesise, route, and program the ICs from Verilog source. The tools work in the way I’m used to toolchains working: read file in, do <em>stuff</em>, write file out. No IDE, no graphical integrated design tool, just source files in text, intermediate files in various formats, and a binary at the end of it all.</p>
<p>All of this settled the matter. I didn’t really need an FPGA on the TRS-20 and in fact it runs just fine with the FPGA sitting there totally inert. Its main functional role is as an interrupt controller: nothing else is wired to the interrupt lines of the processor, and I didn’t want to try making a controller out of discrete logic ICs. I did really want to play with an FPGA, though, so that’s exactly what I’m going to do.</p>
<h1 id="the-basics---building-a-bitstream">The basics - building a bitstream</h1>
<p>I like Make. I’ve used it for decades. It’s far from a perfect tool, and despite having used it for decades it’s in the pile of tools that I wouldn’t be able to use in any non-trivial way if Google were ever offline. But for this sort of task, it’s pretty much perfect. The build process with Project Icestorm takes three steps, each time loading some file(s) from disk and writing further file(s) out to disk.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Synthesise the design using <code>yosys</code></p>
<p>This step takes in one or more Verilog source files and translates it into the building blocks of an FPGA - LUTs, DFFs, I/O ports, and other special cells. The banner image for this post is a little bit of a graph representation of the synthesised design. Here’s an entire component from the design.</p>
<figure>
<img src="/images/edgedetect.png" alt="" /><figcaption>A rising edge detector compares the past state of the signal to its current state</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>The synchronous statement <code class="sourceCode verilog"><span class="kw">always</span> @(<span class="kw">posedge</span> clk) past &lt;= in;</code> establishes that each rising edge of the clock signal will load the input into the <code>past</code> register, while the continuous statement <code class="sourceCode verilog"><span class="kw">assign</span> rise = in &amp; !past;</code> passes the input and the past state through a combinatorial logic circuit. The end result is that at the rising edge of the clock signal <code>rise</code> will be high only when the <code>in</code> signal was low on the last clock edge but is high on the current edge.</p>
<p>The full image for my relatively tiny design is almost unreadably complex. I could see how it may be occasionally useful to trace a particular path with an aim of simplifying the logic involved, but I have not yet done this.</p></li>
<li><p>Place the cells and route connections with <code>nextpnr</code></p>
<p>The synthesised design output by <code>yosys</code> contains all the cells used by the design and the map of how they must be connected. The next stage in getting the design onto silicon is to determine where each cell of the design will lie on the chip and how the routing between them will be arranged. The cells on an FPGA cannot be connected entirely arbitrarily, so the choices of where to place cells and how to connect them become non-trivial. Finding an optimal placement is NP-complete: <code>nextpnr</code> uses simulated annealing to find an approximately optimal solution.</p>
<figure>
<img src="/images/trs20/fpga-layout-miso.png" alt="" /><figcaption>The lower half of an iCE40 with my design placed and routed.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>The image here shows part of the design after packing, placing, and routing has been done. It’s produced by an <a href="https://knielsen.github.io/ice40_viewer/ice40_viewer.html">ICE40 floorplan/layout viewer</a>. The path highlighted in red is the <code>SPI_SDI$SB_IO_IN</code> net - it connects the SPI_SDI I/O buffer in the bottom right to the logic that latches values on the appropriate SPI clock edge.</p></li>
<li><p>Pack the chip configuration data into a bitstream</p>
<p>The <code>icepack</code> tool takes the output of <code>nextpnr</code> and produces a bitstream image. These are always exactly 32,220 bytes in length - and it turns out, they always have a Y-modem CRC of E2B5. This might seem foreboding, like something terrible happens because I comically mix up two images. But no, it’s just a thing - the bitstream format has a CCITT 16-bit CRC checksum in it, the E2B5 is the checksum of the headers and footers. I suppose a different CRC might arise if I used a different combination of options and got a different header.</p>
<p>I also use <code>icemulti</code> at this stage to produce a multi-image bitstream, with four images. This allows the cold boot pins on the CPU board to select one of the images at boot, and the use of the <code>SB_WARMBOOT</code> special cell to reboot into one of them under software control. All four images I packed in were identical for flashing to the ROM: I want the right structure in place to be able to flash a single image into the ROM via the FPGA. I also align all images to 32k boundaries, so I can just erase one 32k sector. The way I’ve set it up places the first image at 0x000a0 with the preceding 160 bytes being the multi-image header. Re-flashing the first image requires that this header is prepended.</p></li>
</ol>
<h1 id="testing-a-hardware-design">Testing a hardware design</h1>
<p>For an extremely simple design like my original “proof-of-concept” LED flasher I can be pretty confident that it’s likely to work first go. As I get more complex I’d like to have more certainty that I’ve got it right than just trusting that I would never make a mistaek.</p>
<p>I frequently see mentions of “testbenches” when doing Google queries like “verilog getting started” and “verilog it doesn’t work help help help”. I’m still not sure what the term means - but it’s an approach for writing an additional Verilog module that provides test inputs to the module under test. In these testbench modules one can use Verilog constructs that have no meaning when synthesised for hardware, such as delaying a specific time period.</p>
<p>I didn’t do any of this.</p>
<p>Instead, I used a tool called <a href="https://www.veripool.org/wiki/verilator">Verilator</a>. This compiles your synthesisable Verilog into C++. Armed with this I wrote a test harness (in C++, I feel so dirty) to validate my design against a fairly simple little script emulating CPU signals for a series of <code>in</code> and <code>out</code> instructions. I also wrote a very basic emulation of an SPI Flash ROM, barely enough to test the timing on the SPI lines.</p>
<p>This not only helped me catch a bunch of errors, it also helped me quickly validate changes as I went.</p>
<p>It also supports writing out a waveform file that can be viewed with a VCD reader like <a href="http://gtkwave.sourceforge.net/">GTKWave</a>.</p>
<figure>
<img src="/images/trs20/gtkwave.png" alt="" /><figcaption>The SPI slave responds to a read request with 0xEF</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Between the test harness and the waveform, I got my SPI code into what looked like good shape pretty quickly.</p>
<h1 id="an-emulator-is-an-approximation">An emulator is an approximation</h1>
<p>But of course, it did not work properly once it hit hardware. Part of the problem is that the FPGA puts the flash IC into power down state once its done, so the only thing it will respond to is a wake-up command, but my code was instead trying to send the manufacturer ID command. Once I fixed that up - it still didn’t work properly. But it was clear it was transmitting properly, because it woke up and responded to the manufacturer ID command. The response was shifted by one bit. This is a pretty common error in SPI implementations - it’s indicative of a clocking fault.</p>
<p>The SPI chip is rated up to 133MHz for all instructions except Read Data, which is rated up to 50MHz. I didn’t exactly design this part of the board with high clock speeds in mind: I know it’s good at 40MHz, which is the speed the FPGA reads from it. My design only pushes it at 50MHz, by toggling the <code>SPI_CLK</code> line high and low on each rising edge of the 100MHz global clock.</p>
<p>There’s useful information given by <code>nextpnr</code> when it lays out your design for the IC: timing approximations for critical paths. One of my critical paths is the asynchronous inputs feeding into the 100MHz clock domain - it takes up to 7.3ns for <code>D2</code> to meander through a handful of cells before reaching the input of a flip-flop clocked in that domain. Another is the time it takes for a signal to go from the output of a flip-flop in the 100MHz domain to the <code>SPI_SS</code> output pin - this is 4.6ns, most of which is just the time it takes for the signal to traverse the various routing components involved in going from one side of the FPGA to the other.</p>
<p>4.6ns is the slowest such signal, which means that both <code>SPI_SCK</code> and <code>SPI_SDI</code> take less time than that. At 50MHz there’s 10ns available from the falling edge when the SPI flash will shift to the rising edge when the FPGA will latch. In theory there shouldn’t be a timing problem. The ROM’s datasheet says it’s at most 6ns after the falling edge of the clock signal before output data is valid - it’s possible it just takes more than 10ns for data to be stabilised and routed. Unlikely, but possible.</p>
<p>I slowed the SPI clock down to 25MHz, and lo! it worked.</p>
<p>However, it also occurred to me that I was latching input when the output clock signal was low but about to go high. This “rising edge” was clear and sharp on the inside of the FPGA, but of course it takes time for that signal to reach the edge of the device and from there get out to the ROM. Likewise, the falling edge takes time to be seen. I switched over to latching the input on the same clock edge that I lower SCK and shift data - this takes into account the delays for signals to move into and out of the FPGA. I think this is how people with experience in this space do it… but I did it myself to learn stuff, like how to see the accumulated delays for paths through the FPGA.</p>
<p>With the clock back up to 50MHz, I tried again… and to my giggly glee, it still worked.</p>
<h1 id="faster-and-faster">Faster and faster</h1>
<p>Moving to 100Mhz would be a little tricky: I could possibly just <code class="sourceCode verilog"><span class="kw">assign</span> SPI_SCK = CLK;</code> and basically wire the 100MHz clock directly to the master clock. When I look at how others are doing it, I see tricks like using <a href="https://zipcpu.com/blog/2018/08/16/spiflash.html">DDR cells</a> to toggle the SPI clock on rising and falling edges, with an enable signal to shut it off.</p>
<p>It’s also not really necessary. I added wait state generation - you can see the <code>waitstate</code> signal in the waveform above. One thing to note about wait state generation on the TRS-20 is that it passes through a DFF IC, clocked by the rising edge of <code>PHI</code>. This IC has its own setup time that means the FPGA shouldn’t change <code>/WAIT</code> arbitrarily: it needs to change at least 3ns before <code>PHI</code> rises. I approach this with a rising edge detector on <code>PHI</code> - this is stabilised to CLK and could be up to 20ns behind the real rising edge, which is still ~30ns before the next one.</p>
<p>However, for an I/O operation the CPU will sample <code>/WAIT</code> on the falling edge of the first wait state. The DFF in the way means I need to assert <code>/WAIT</code> before the rising edge of that wait state. Having enough time to guarantee detection of it is implausible with my current approach.</p>
<p><code>/IORQ</code> and <code>/RD</code> will fall up to 25ns after the falling edge of T1. I’ll detect them up to 20ns after that - 45ns after the falling edge of T1. T2 will have risen by then, and could rise even before <code>/IORQ</code> and <code>/RD</code> have both fallen. To catch the read request I could insert an additional cycle on the <code>PHI</code> edge detect so that always comes after the read request control signals. But <code>/WR</code> falls up to 25ns after the rising edge of T2, and I won’t detect it until 45ns later. The rising edge of Tw shouldn’t come sooner than 54ns later. That’s only 6ns left to assert <code>/WAIT</code>, which is pushing up pretty hard against the FPGA’s output delays - and assumes any input delays don’t wind up adding one clock cycle to the stabilisers. Which they will.</p>
<p>A second edition of my CPU board might fix this with something like removing the DFF for <code>/WAIT</code> - the setup time for the signal is 15ns before <code>PHI</code> falls. That would give me a bit longer to get <code>/WAIT</code> in order, probably long enough to solve the problem. Another option that’s appealing is to synchronise the clocks - run the CPU at 20Mhz and use a PLL to run the FPGA at 100Mhz with a shared edge. The HX1K doesn’t have a PLL in the VQFP-100 package though, so I’d also have to go to the HX4K in the TQFP-144 package or pay a hefty fee to get a fab house to solder a BGA package on for me. I can’t divide the 100MHz clock down to drive the CPU, because the CPU runs its own clock generator, and I’ve no idea how well synchronised the <code>PHI</code> output is to the <code>EXTAL</code> input.</p>
<p>For now I’ll just accept the need to have a minimum of one wait state configured on the CPU for I/O.</p>
<p>Another way to get faster results is to use dual I/O mode. I didn’t wire up enough pins to use quad I/O mode, so dual is my limit, but it would give me an effective 100MHz data rate. Doing so requires that the FPGA understands the SPI command set - it needs to know to change outputs to inputs at the right time to avoid frying pins on either FPGA or ROM. Because frying the FPGA’s SPI pins would be such a big ol’ pile of suck I’ve got it actively preventing the dual and quad I/O commands right now. I don’t need it fast as much as I need it not to ruin the part that took me three attempts to solder properly.</p>
<h1 id="the-cpu-board-is-done">The CPU board is done</h1>
<p>The last change to push the clock back up to 50Mhz did not involve removing the flash ROM to reprogram it. Instead, I programmed it at 25MHz. The CPU board is now wholly self-sufficient: I have CP/M commands that will reprogram the ROMs for both the CPU and the FPGA.</p>
<p>The TRS-20 now needs non-volatile file storage. I could probably do something with the excess capacity of the FPGA’s ROM, there’s 3.8Mb to be had. This would involve doing deblocking in the CP/M BIOS and being cautious not to write to it willy-nilly because I’d have no load wearing. Better to look at connecting up an SD card - but whether I choose to design a second revision of the board with the SD card on it or go to a daughter board is still not certain.</p>
<p>Since writing the bulk of this post I went on to update my <a href="https://github.com/codebje/fpga20">FPGA code</a> to support an SD card on external pins. I wound up making my SPI driver asynchronous to the bus: a write begins an SPI exchange, a read returns the value latched from the last exchange (and, optionally, begins another). At 25MHz or higher this happens faster than the CPU can read I/O and write RAM. For both the SD card (at 25MHz) and the Flash ROM (at 50MHz) this gives me bulk reads using <code>inir</code> - but to support this I had to give up my 16-bit I/O addressing and live within 8 bits instead. Replacing the genuine CP/M 2.2 with ZSDOS and ZCPR1 (from <a href="https://github.com/davidgiven/cpmish">CP/Mish</a>) is next on my to-do list, including supporting deblocking and an SD card disk driver.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Operating systems</title>
    <link href="https://bje.id.au/blog/posts/trs20/017-operating-system.html" />
    <id>https://bje.id.au/blog/posts/trs20/017-operating-system.html</id>
    <published>2020-10-13T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-10-13T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My computer has reached the point that I can run arbitrary code on it. Having sorted out how to get a decent chunk of arbitrary code onto the device without removing the Flash ROM and using <a href="013-program-roms.html">frankenprogrammer</a> I’ve turned my attention to what I should run on it.</p>
<p>The TRS-20 is supposed to be able to run old software to tickle my nostalgia. I don’t intend to write everything myself: if I don’t think I’ll learn from it, or have fun with it, I’ll use what already exists. This applies in the case of the operating system, where there’s a wealth of options available for retrobrew Z80/Z180 computers.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>My original TRS-80 Model I didn’t have a disk drive, and so it didn’t have a disk operating system. Instead it had a built-in BASIC interpreter and a tape cassette interface for loading programs. Machine language programs were supported, through trickery I don’t recall using. But, all that aside, I’ve no particular desire to take my nostalgia trip so far as to limit myself to TRS-80 Level 1 BASIC.</p>
<p>The banner image is (as it clearly says) TRSDOS, which I never ran. It might be possible to run it, but I don’t see much reason to try - early versions are extremely limited, and I am not sitting on a trove of TRS-80 software I’m itching to run that would need something it provides.</p>
<p>So we move on to CP/M, the dominant disk operating system of the Z80 era. For those unfamiliar with it, as I was, it’s the progenitor of the venerable MS-DOS: Microsoft’s classic operating system reimplemented large parts of CP/M, accusations were made, unpleasantness abounded, long story short Digital Research didn’t last but Microsoft did. The rights for CP/M bounced around for a while, and eventually the company holding them granted a license to the <a href="http://www.cpm.z80.de/">Unofficial CP/M Web Site</a> to distribute the CP/M source code, amongst other things. So CP/M appears perfectly valid to run.</p>
<p>CP/M’s popularity means there is vast amounts of software written for it. Enthusiasts have kept large archives of the stuff online for decades. Some of it is probably going to be worth running… and CP/M 2.2 is easy to port to a Z180 retrobrew system like mine.</p>
<p>Other alternatives include <a href="http://fuzix.org/">Fuzix</a>, a UNIX for 8-bit processors. It has appeal - but there’s a lot of work involved in porting it to new machines, and I think it’s likely to be permanently in development. On top of that, it’s a ton of C code and expects application software to also be C code, and I’m just not all that keen to pick up an obligation to write more C these days.</p>
<p>There’s also <a href="https://github.com/wwarthen/RomWBW">RomWBW</a> which packs a lot into a ROM image: MMU-capable BIOS, support for CP/M 2.2, CP/M 3, ZSDOS 1.1, NZCOM, ZPM3, and some variant of FreeRTOS. It expects a 512K or 1024K ROM, though, and expects ROM to be at physical address 0, RAM at physical address $80000 - the exact opposite of the TRS-20. This assumption is hard-coded in multiple places. It does have nice ideas for a Z180 BIOS to consider: stubs in the 64K space invoking the MMU to jump to larger functions, for example.</p>
<p>In the end, just a plain old CP/M 2.2 is the most plausible starting point. There’s a <a href="http://cpuville.com/Code/CPM-on-a-new-computer.html">solid guide</a> for porting it to a new Z80 machine, too. So I added a CP/M BIOS to my <a href="https://github.com/codebje/trs20-bootrom">boot ROM code</a>, along with a 32Kb ROM disk. The boot code formats a 192Kb RAM disk as well, giving me a large working area. CP/M itself consists of two parts: the BDOS that stays resident while transient programs run, and the CCP command processor that is reloaded on every warm boot.</p>
<h1 id="running-cpm-on-the-trs-20">Running CP/M on the TRS-20</h1>
<p>To bootstrap this into operation, I used my <a href="https://github.com/codebje/isp-writer">isp-writer</a> project to copy the new boot ROM plus CP/M into the second 64Kb of RAM, patch various locations in it accordingly, then use it to boot CP/M. From there, I wrote a <a href="https://github.com/codebje/cpmsuite/blob/master/src/sst.asm">small tool</a> to write a file into the Flash ROM, and installed the new ROM image. Satisfying.</p>
<p>In the Virtual TRS-20, I wound up doing something slightly different. The VTRS-20 uses ZSDOS and ZCPR as distributed by David Given in <a href="https://github.com/davidgiven/cpmish">cpmish</a>. On my unwritten TODO list for the TRS-20 is to replace CP/M 2.2 with ZSDOS and ZCPR - which will work out easiest if I rewrite my boot code and be more flexible about loading a BDOS and a CCP from fixed locations in ROM. This will let me update all the parts individually in Flash, rather than building a single image.</p>
<p>The VTRS-20 now supports running a CP/M command file directly from the command line, or booting into a CP/M shell with a set of files pre-loaded into the RAM drive.</p>
<p>The last few posts have been a bit of a catch-up exercise in documenting what I’ve done. From the blog alone, it may appear that after I first got some life out of the CPU board everything more or less stopped - but in truth I’ve been playing around with one aspect or another of the board since then, so much that I’ve fallen far behind on writing up what I’ve done. One consequence of that is that these last couple of posts have been written more out of a desire to just get some words committed to files than with any particular attention to editing. I’ve also been working on a LISP interpreter (because it seems like a fun thing to write) and being able to program the FPGA in-system - so perhaps my next few posts will be a bit less dry. I also still owe myself a final reckoning for how much I’ve spent on this project so far, and how much it would cost to build a CPU board given what I know now, so there’s at least one more rather dull post coming.</p>
<p>The TRS-20 is currently running 24/7, with its USB UART connected to a Raspberry Pi. I got heartily sick of fussing with two USB cables to both power and communicate with the device, and took a brief look into possible Bluetooth UART modules, before realising I could just SSH to the Pi and leave the thing plugged in permanently so I can play with it any time. Which works fine, until I lock it up with some shonky code and have to yank power to reset it. Eventually that might irritate me enough to make a remote reboot facility. Or at least try to sort out a reset button somehow.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Running code on the TRS-20</title>
    <link href="https://bje.id.au/blog/posts/trs20/016-running-code.html" />
    <id>https://bje.id.au/blog/posts/trs20/016-running-code.html</id>
    <published>2020-10-11T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-10-11T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After proving that my computer board actually works, it’s time to switch over to software design. This is my core competency, where I’ve spent years professionally, and something I’ve done as a hobby since before I even had a computer. You’d think this part would be easy…</p>
<!--more-->
<p>On the <a href="https://github.com/codebje/vtrs20">Virtual TRS-20</a>, the boot rom starts up, accepts a Y-modem upload, and then jumps to it, happy as Larry. On the real TRS-20, the Y-modem upload fails on the first packet, with nothing more than metadata sent.</p>
<p>The emulator is reasonably faithful to the behaviour of the TRS-20 as I discover its nuances. Memory reads now carry an /M1 flag to allow the ROM masking to more accurately replicate the board, though I didn’t go as far as emulating the timing issue. It’s useful when debugging the boot ROM code as I can stop it, inspect memory and registers, single-step it with ease, and <em>in theory</em> get code working before it hits the real device where debugging is much harder.</p>
<p>In the case of the Y-modem upload, this isn’t the case.</p>
<h1 id="on-with-the-debug">On with the debug</h1>
<p>During the serial debug described in the <a href="015-testing-continues.html">last post</a> I found one possibly significant difference between what I expected to happen and what really happens. The <code>/RTS0</code> signal is not asserted automatically by the Z180 when its own ASCI0 receive buffer is full. The signal is entirely up to software - so I cannot rely on it to prevent overruns when uploading bytes. It may be that I’m dropping bits by blasting Y-modem packets at the CPU as fast as the UART can handle them.</p>
<p>The heart of my Y-modem code is the <code>recv_packet</code> function. The general idea is that it waits for a packet command byte for up to five seconds, then (re)transmits the ACK code assuming the sender didn’t receive it. After that, if it’s a data packet it receives the packet index then the data, with a timeout of one second for each byte. On completion it checks that the CRC matches.</p>
<p>I can work out a lot about what’s going on using some black-box probing of the behaviour. Not transmitting anything gets ‘C’ repeated every five seconds until it gives up after ten failures (‘C’ is used for the first packet to indicate CRC-mode, rather than an ACK). Sending an invalid command byte does the same, but faster. Sending a valid data packet byte <em>appears</em> to work - but then fails. After that, both the number of retry attempts and the ACK byte are corrupted.</p>
<p>This suggests the CRC function isn’t working.</p>
<p>It also suggests I have a way to keep going without removing the IC and flashing new code. The metadata packet is received before the CRC error kicks in, after which the transfer can be aborted with 2x<code>CAN</code>. The metadata packet, however, is stored right where the first data packet should subsequently get written to - and where the boot monitor will jump when executing uploaded code. Using the 1024-byte packet command this gives me a full 1026 bytes of data (packet plus two CRC bytes) that I can upload and execute.</p>
<p>Using a combination of uploading bits of code to run and replacement editions of <code>recv_packet</code> to patch in place of the boot code version, I tracked down my <em>multiple</em> errors. I present them here in source file order, but this is not the order I discovered them.</p>
<h1 id="timeouts-dont-stop-the-transfer">Timeouts don’t stop the transfer</h1>
<p>Failing ten times should abort the transfer. But it doesn’t - the code just keeps on spitting out retry bytes. Eventually I tracked this down to the following few lines of code:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb1"><pre class="sourceCode z80asm"><code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span id="cb1-1"><a href="#cb1-1"></a><span class="fu">retry:</span>		djnz	metadata</span>
<span id="cb1-2"><a href="#cb1-2"></a></span>
<span id="cb1-3"><a href="#cb1-3"></a><span class="fu">done:</span>		pop	<span class="at">hl</span></span>
<span id="cb1-4"><a href="#cb1-4"></a>		pop	<span class="at">de</span></span>
<span id="cb1-5"><a href="#cb1-5"></a>		ret</span></code></pre></div>
<p>A successful run through the code jumps to <code>done</code> with the zero flag reset. An unsuccessful run jumps to <code>done</code> with the zero flag set. I thought that <code class="sourceCode z80asm">djnz</code> would set the zero flag - but instead it doesn’t affect flags at all. Whatever the zero flag was on entry to <code>retry</code> is what it will be after the <code class="sourceCode z80asm">djnz</code> has decremented <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="at">b</span></code> to zero. Just adding <code class="sourceCode z80asm">xor <span class="at">a</span></code> will set the zero flag.</p>
<h1 id="the-retry-byte-gets-corrupted">The retry byte gets corrupted</h1>
<p>After attempting to send a valid (meta)data packet the retry byte becomes corrupted. After a failed packet transfer instead of getting a ‘C’ back I start getting NULs. I tracked this down to the code invoked after a data packet command is received.</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb2"><pre class="sourceCode z80asm"><code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span id="cb2-1"><a href="#cb2-1"></a><span class="fu">recv_body:</span>	ld	(cmd), <span class="at">a</span></span>
<span id="cb2-2"><a href="#cb2-2"></a>		ld	<span class="at">de</span>, <span class="bn">1</span>*<span class="bn">100</span></span>
<span id="cb2-3"><a href="#cb2-3"></a>		call	recv_byte</span>
<span id="cb2-4"><a href="#cb2-4"></a>		jr	z, retry</span>
<span id="cb2-5"><a href="#cb2-5"></a>		ld	<span class="at">c</span>, <span class="at">a</span></span>
<span id="cb2-6"><a href="#cb2-6"></a>		call	recv_byte</span>
<span id="cb2-7"><a href="#cb2-7"></a>		jr	z, retry</span>
<span id="cb2-8"><a href="#cb2-8"></a>		cpl</span>
<span id="cb2-9"><a href="#cb2-9"></a>		cp	<span class="at">a</span>, <span class="at">c</span></span>
<span id="cb2-10"><a href="#cb2-10"></a>		jr	nz, retry</span>
<span id="cb2-11"><a href="#cb2-11"></a>		ld	(seq), <span class="at">a</span></span></code></pre></div>
<p>The problem, of course, is that I assumed early on that <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="at">c</span></code> would be preserved as my retry byte value, and subsequently also decided to use <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="at">c</span></code> to store the sequence number to compare to its complement. Oops. I accepted that there’s not many registers on the Z180 and stored the retry byte in memory instead.</p>
<h1 id="going-too-far-the-other-way">Going too far the other way</h1>
<p>Now we come to the headline problem - the CRC validation is failing. The other problems would happen in emulation, if I’d exhaustively tested all possible code paths. My <code class="sourceCode z80asm">djnz</code> emulation didn’t set flags. Yes, that’s right, I wrote assembly code that assumed one thing about an instruction, and code to emulate that instruction assuming something else. People are fallible, tests never exhaustively test all possible code paths, and trusting to discipline to catch problems is naive.</p>
<p>But this problem was different: the bytes were being received correctly. I could send binary code and run it, which wouldn’t be possible if the transfer were corrupted. The CRC code works fine when testing. There’s only one answer left: the CRC code isn’t being called correctly.</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb3"><pre class="sourceCode z80asm"><code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span id="cb3-1"><a href="#cb3-1"></a>		push	<span class="at">hl</span></span>
<span id="cb3-2"><a href="#cb3-2"></a>		push	<span class="at">bc</span></span>
<span id="cb3-3"><a href="#cb3-3"></a></span>
<span id="cb3-4"><a href="#cb3-4"></a>		ld	<span class="at">bc</span>, <span class="bn">130</span></span>
<span id="cb3-5"><a href="#cb3-5"></a>		ld	<span class="at">a</span>, (cmd)</span>
<span id="cb3-6"><a href="#cb3-6"></a>		cp	<span class="at">a</span>, YM_SOH</span>
<span id="cb3-7"><a href="#cb3-7"></a>		jr	z, <span class="bn">$</span>+<span class="bn">5</span></span>
<span id="cb3-8"><a href="#cb3-8"></a>		ld	<span class="at">bc</span>, <span class="bn">1026</span></span>
<span id="cb3-9"><a href="#cb3-9"></a></span>
<span id="cb3-10"><a href="#cb3-10"></a>		ld	<span class="at">de</span>, <span class="bn">1</span>*<span class="bn">100</span></span>
<span id="cb3-11"><a href="#cb3-11"></a>		call	recv_wait</span>
<span id="cb3-12"><a href="#cb3-12"></a></span>
<span id="cb3-13"><a href="#cb3-13"></a>		pop	<span class="at">bc</span></span>
<span id="cb3-14"><a href="#cb3-14"></a>		pop	<span class="at">hl</span></span></code></pre></div>
<p>This little bit of code is responsible for receiving either 130 or 1026 bytes, the payload and its CRC, depending on whether it’s a SOH or STX command. I carefully preserve <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="at">bc</span></code> because <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="at">b</span></code> contains my retry counter and <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="at">c</span></code> contains (hah!) my retry byte. Then I set up <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="at">bc</span></code> to hold the size of the payload and CRC, and receive the data.</p>
<p>Then I restore <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="at">bc</span></code>.</p>
<p>At this point in receiving the metadata packet <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="at">bc</span></code> contains <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="bn">$0a00</span></code>. There are still ten retries allowed, and the retry byte has been replaced by NUL. The payload length I calculated is gone.</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb4"><pre class="sourceCode z80asm"><code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span id="cb4-1"><a href="#cb4-1"></a>		jr	z, retry</span>
<span id="cb4-2"><a href="#cb4-2"></a>		call	ym_crc		<span class="co">; CRC should be zero</span></span></code></pre></div>
<p>Then I call the CRC code. This expects the data to checksum in <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="at">hl</span></code> (check: I preserved <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="at">hl</span></code> for exactly this reason) and the length of the data in <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="at">bc</span></code> … but that’s not the length of the received data any more. It’s much, much bigger than the received data.</p>
<p>The Y-modem 16-bit CRC isn’t the world’s best choice of checksum. It’s definitely an improvement over X-modem’s naive 8-bit checksum but it’s a long way short of a reliable hash. In this case one simple flaw plays out: <code class="sourceCode c">crc16(<span class="dv">0</span>, <span class="dv">0</span>) == <span class="dv">0</span></code>.</p>
<p>My emulator’s SRAM is initialised to zero. Real SRAM is initialised to the background noise of the universe. On my emulator, I checksum 2560 bytes and come up with the same answer I would if I only checksummed the first 130 or 1026 bytes: zero. On the real board the CRC computes over 130 or 1026 bytes of data, getting zero - and then goes on to incorporate the noise.</p>
<p>Well - SRAM’s initial state isn’t actually noise. It’s the consequence of unstable states in (more-or-less) flip-flops resolving one way or the other, which usually comes down to microscopic manufacturing differences. As a result, I always get the <em>same</em> wrong value, because my SRAM on power-on always got the <em>same</em> uninitialised junk in it.</p>
<p>Nifty.</p>
<h1 id="fixing-it-all">Fixing it all</h1>
<p>I wrote a <a href="https://github.com/codebje/scomm">simple program</a> to transmit a patch for <code>recv_packet</code>, then do a full Y-modem transfer of something bigger.</p>
<p>The code for this, I called the <a href="https://github.com/codebje/isp-writer/blob/ymodem-patch/src/ispwriter.asm">in-system programming writer</a>.</p>
<p>At ths point, I can patch the bad code to upload up to 52k of arbitrary code and run it. But it’s not too satisfying to just have a low effort boot monitor with a Y-modem upload for running new code, so rather than focusing on updating the Flash ROM itself the next task will be to upload an operating system.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>The TRS-20 - Will it work?</title>
    <link href="https://bje.id.au/blog/posts/trs20/015-testing-continues.html" />
    <id>https://bje.id.au/blog/posts/trs20/015-testing-continues.html</id>
    <published>2020-08-01T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-08-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With the board fully assembled, and USB enumeration working well enough to see the device, it’s time to see if the design is valid. Do I have a working Z180-based computer, or an expensive paperweight?</p>
<!--more-->
<h1 id="first-blink-the-lights">First, blink the lights</h1>
<p>My <a href="https://github.com/codebje/trs20-bootrom">initial bootrom</a> changes the CPU clock divider from EXTAL/2 to EXTAL/1 a few bytes into execution. With the FPGA reprogrammed to flash LED1 on a 24-bit divider, a 9.216MHz PHI will blink LED1 at 0.55Hz and an 18.432MHz PHI will blink it at 1.1Hz. With LED2 still on a 26-bit divider of the 100MHz oscillator, this provides an easy to observe visual guide to whether my boot ROM is executing at all.</p>
<p>Which lead me to discover that my boot ROM was not executing at all. The CPU was putting out a clock signal just fine, but at 9.216MHz, not 18.432MHz.</p>
<p>To verify the CPU was still okay after all my earlier fumbling about I put it back into the old debug board I built early on in the process, with an 18.432MHz can oscillator. My logic analyser showed it doing the expected signal dance - but I also recorded what happened as the CPU came out of /RESET, and saw that A19 stays high after /RESET has gone high. It stubbornly doesn’t fall until the address lines are being settled for the first machine cycle, which is up to 30ns after PHI rises for clock cycle T1. On top of that /M1 falls at most 35ns after PHI rises for T1. To the limits of accuracy of my very cheap 24MHz analyser, in practice /M1 falls at the same time as A19.</p>
<p>This is a significant oversight in my board design - the datasheet shows, if you look properly, that /M1 could fall before the address lines have settled. An earlier revision of my design used /MREQ instead of /M1, which can be seen in <a href="011-motherboard.html#memory">the design post</a> diagram. Despite my excessively detailed blog posts I neglected to document why I changed to /M1, but I believe it’s because I only wanted execution accesses to ROM to trigger the flip-flop. If I’d stuck with /MREQ then A19 would be settled low before /MREQ goes low, and this would have gone a bit smoother.</p>
<p>The consequence of all this is that the ROM overlay DFF is reset before the first memory read even happens, and ROM never gets read.</p>
<p>The good news is that there’s a simple fix to get the ROM overlay active at boot: I’ve put a 10kΩ 0603 resistor between the A19 and GND pins of the CPU socket, underneath the board. This pulls A19 low during reset, and it’s still low when /M1 falls for the first opcode fetch. Thereafter, the CPU continues to hold A19 low for each access.</p>
<p>With this fix in place, the LED starts to blink at twice the speed. I now have a computer that can run code!</p>
<h1 id="communication">Communication?</h1>
<p>After adjusting the clock speed the boot code’s next task is to set up ASCI0. As the ROM progresses from here it prints out the character sequence ‘1234567’, with each character indicating successful completion of another step of the boot-up.</p>
<p>Perhaps predictably by now, my serial terminal remained stubbornly blank. No output at all - but due to another questionable design choice, I wasn’t sure this meant the boot code was failing to transmit a character or not. This time it was the fact that the /RESET line also resets the FT230X USB IC. This causes the serial port to disconnect and reconnect; the FT230X datasheet doesn’t specify a time range for this but it will read the internal memory to configure the USB descriptors, enumerate as a USB device, and negotiate a connection. That’s enough work to be a non-trivial amount of time.</p>
<p>So - with no way to talk to the CPU to find out what’s going on, I resorted to the logic analyser. My analyser has eight lines, so it cannot monitor the entire bus at once, but it can watch some pins and check they’re behaving. I checked the ROM’s /CE and /OE pins, which were firing properly. I checked, rechecked, triple checked, and dispiritedly checked the ASCI0 lines to the FT230X. Without a reset button, I resorted to five second samples at a slow rate, before finally cluing in that I could pull /WAIT low through the bus header, and freeze the CPU to inspect what it was doing.</p>
<p>Freezing the CPU after it had run for a little while showed it had gone out to lunch in the middle of memory where no predictable value could be expected. It also showed that the transceiver pin for A12 was poorly soldered, but while that needed fixing it wasn’t in a position to be causing any faults.</p>
<p>Freezing the CPU before it finished the first opcode fetch showed the right values on address and data lines.</p>
<p>So - somewhere in between the first byte read, and thousands of cycles later, the CPU goes a bit nuts.</p>
<h1 id="debugging-a-cpu-board">Debugging a CPU board</h1>
<p>It’s impractical to try and whip a jumper lead in and out of the /WAIT header and expect to see anything meaningful going on. However, my board has a powerful tool available on in the form of the FPGA. Most of the board’s signals are connected to an FPGA pin so it has broad insight into the workings of the CPU. It also has a view of the /WAIT signal.</p>
<p>What it does need is a way to tell me what’s going on. Since the FPGA is expected to eventually run an I2C bus, I thought it’d be convenient to give it an I2C slave interface for a µC to drive. The FPGA can drive /WAIT low when /MREQ or /IORQ falls, capture address and data lines, and send all that information to the µC in a four byte burst.</p>
<p>Rather than trying to greenfields my own I2C module, I read over a handful of existing implementations. In the end I used one by Daniel Beer that has <a href="https://dlbeer.co.nz/articles/i2c.html">a truly excellent explanation</a>. Since it’s unlicensed, my FPGA code for this single step debugger is unpublished, but it’s not rocket surgery. I did get to learn about crossing clock domains though, to have an effective signal between an I2C event indicating the CPU should proceed to the next instruction and the CPU’s <em>much faster</em> clock cycle.</p>
<p>This work uncovered a bad solder job on A5 of the FPGA, which I also fixed. And amazingly, I had completely failed to solder one side of one of the I2C pull-up resistors. I hope that’s it for bad solder jobs, because the volume of them makes a mockery of the amount of connectivity testing I did.</p>
<p>The FPGA sends /MREQ, /IORQ, /RD, /RW, and the high four bits of the address bus in the first byte. The next two bytes are the rest of the address bus, and the data bus follows. After all four bytes have been read, the CPU is permitted to proceed.</p>
<p>On the µC side of things I just used an ESP8266 as a convenient 3v3 device, and programmed it using Arduino IDE. After a few iterations I wound up with something that could single step, run a number of steps, run to an address access, and set breakpoints. Its output looks something like this:</p>
<pre><code>MiRw 0016D  ED (11101101)
MiRw 0016E  39 (00111001)
MiRw 0016F  38 (00111000)</code></pre>
<p>… which is the CPU fetching and executing <code class="sourceCode z80asm">out0 (CBR), <span class="at">a</span></code>.</p>
<p>The debug tool showed that without a USB connection, the boot ROM pauses waiting for the transmit data register empty (TDRE) flag to be set for ASCI0. When that flag is set, the CPU writes ‘1’ - and the serial terminal receives it. This confirms my hunch that the USB IC is still resetting when the CPU starts writing to it. And confirms that the serial link works!</p>
<p>I had mixed up my boot code somehow and tried to do the MMU work right in the middle of setting up the DMA registers. Once I fixed this, I could watch the DMA executing its copy loop, reading from ROM and writing to RAM byte by byte.</p>
<p>I also discovered that the MMU base registers are added to the logical address: if Common Area 1 starts at <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="bn">$F000</span></code> with a base register of <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="bn">$80</span></code> the physical address is <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="bn">$8F000</span></code>. This makes sense from an implementation perspective - it’s a single 8-bit adder involved - and was an easy fix to set CBAR to <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="bn">$71</span></code> instead.</p>
<p>The remaining consequences of my choice to use /M1 then became apparent. A memory access to ROM space would set A19 high, with /M1 also high, no problem so far. But the next machine cycle would lower /M1 at around the same time as A19, with enough overlap between them for my flip-flop to be reset. The safest action is to jump to ROM as soon as possible, without allowing any other access to ROM space to happen first.</p>
<p>I re-ordered the boot code to set up the MMU first, jumped to ROM space, ran the DMA copy from there, then jumped back to, in theory, SRAM.</p>
<p>A transmit test that modified code showed that yes, I had code running out of SRAM.</p>
<h1 id="rough-consensus-and-running-code"><del>Rough consensus and</del> running code</h1>
<p>Let’s take a moment to absorb this.</p>
<p>I have a <em>working computer</em>. It has boot ROM, working memory, and enough peripherals for me to interact with it.</p>
<p>There’s plenty more to do from here, the Y-modem upload doesn’t work, I have nothing useful to upload, the FPGA isn’t capable of self-programming yet, and there are other boards I expect to add on over time. There’s even a laundry list of things I’d do differently on a second revision of the CPU board.</p>
<p>But none of that matters just as this exact moment: demonstrating running code on the board means this project is now a success.</p>
<p><img src="/images/trs20/logo.svg" /></p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>The TRS-20 - Finishing assembly</title>
    <link href="https://bje.id.au/blog/posts/trs20/014-finish-assembly.html" />
    <id>https://bje.id.au/blog/posts/trs20/014-finish-assembly.html</id>
    <published>2020-07-21T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-07-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I claimed in the last post that, with blinking lights achieved, the job was done.</p>
<p>Of course, the job is not really done. Most of the board’s parts aren’t soldered on, and while it’s great that the FPGA works I’ve still yet to get the CPU on. Not to mention all the supporting chips. Time to break out the heat gun and get on with the task.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>I put on the FT230X USB IC first, plus its supporting connector and passives. This is for two reasons: I can program the GPIOs on it to ensure the correct VBus sense function and LED output, and because this is the last checkpoint beore I solder on every other part. This worked out fine - the device enumerates correctly, programs fine, and the RX LED flickers in time to keystrokes via USB serial.</p>
<figure>
<img src="/images/trs20/enumerated.png" alt="" /><figcaption>My shell history is chockers full of <code>lsusb</code> commands now.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Soldering everything else took a few evenings. My process was to squeeze a blob of solder paste onto the DDPAK tab copper area on a board with a bad FPGA solder job, align the target IC with its pads, then use a toothpick to place a sparing amount of paste on the pins. The heat gun then melts the paste onto the pins, and any faults are touched up with the iron.</p>
<figure>
<img src="/images/trs20/memory-pins.jpg" alt="" /><figcaption>I really should get some kind of macro lens for this stuff.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>The best result was the SRAM. It’s possible there’s not quite enough solder on these pins, but I tested every one - I actually found two cold solder joints on the FPGA during this process - and I’m confident they’re all wetted properly.</p>
<p>The worst result was the 18.432MHz oscillator. I underestimated the difficulty of this job, and wound up with far too much solder on it. Solder from the NC pad reached the ground-connected case, and removing it was difficult. I do not feel confident that this part is healthy now.</p>
<h2 id="install-a-rom">Install a ROM</h2>
<p>The trouble with having finished the soldering is that I don’t much want to blindly power up. The ROM should contain <code>FF</code> endlessly, which will result in the CPU executing <code class="sourceCode z80asm">RST <span class="bn">$38</span></code> forever, but it’d be nice to be able to verify in some way that everything’s working as it should. This takes me back to writing a ROM again, but this time for the CPU.</p>
<p>So I wrote a <a href="https://github.com/codebje/trs20-bootrom/blob/master/src/bootrom.asm">ROM image</a> that sets up ASCI0 to 38400 baud, 8n1, and starts transmitting single character “printf debugging” style progress markers. The only things I do first are to disable DRAM refresh, disable external interrupts, and set the clock rate to the full oscillator speed.</p>
<p>After that, the boot ROM attempts to copy ROM into RAM, reset the ROM overlay D flip-flop, configure the MMU, set up a 100Hz timer, set up a stack, then run a very simple boot monitor that permits a binary to be uploaded using ymodem and executed.</p>
<p>Because I really don’t want to yank the PLCC-32 ROM chip in and out frequently, I don’t want too many rounds of corrections. My <a href="https://github.com/codebje/vtrs20">emulator</a> is therefore developing more or less in lockstep with the needs of the boot ROM so that I at least have to implement the same bug twice in more or less the same way to miss it. This is a feat I have accomplished in the past, and it’s surprisingly easy to do.</p>
<p>I burned the ROM, plugged it into the board, and with bated breath powered the board up. Good news: the FLT light doesn’t immediately go on, so there’s no major short circuit anywhere. The FPGA still blinks its LED, and the rest sits there, reminding me that I didn’t design in an obvious indicator of CPU health.</p>
<p>I plugged the USART USB cable in, and …</p>
<p><img src="/images/trs20/whereswally.png" /></p>
<p>… used some adult language.</p>
<h2 id="debugging-a-usb-ic">Debugging a USB IC</h2>
<p>Nothing felt warm. The FLT light was still off. The FPGA was still blinking its LED, now looking more like a taunt than a sign of success.</p>
<p>I busted out the multimeter and did a bit of a probe around, carefully - there’s 3V3 and GND pins right next to each other on the FT230X - only to see all the expected levels. The reset supervisor is not touching /RESET, so it is pulled high by a resistor. The USB cable is delivering ~5V to the voltage divider network. With power removed, I rechecked everything for good solder joints or shorts - everything seems fine.</p>
<p>At a loss, I thought I may as well also test whether the CPU is at least clocking along, so I ran a logic analyser on PHI (and /RESET, to verify the supervisor at the logic level) - and saw only a flat line. The clock was not ticking. It turns out the oscillator just isn’t at all happy, and is not generating any signals. It may still have a short, it may just be toast, either way it’s gotta come off.</p>
<p>I’ve never had much luck desoldering through-hole parts. Solder wick takes a <em>lot</em> of heat to work, and isn’t great even then. My solder sucker was bundled with a cheap soldering iron, and was broken on arrival. I never replaced it. So with a bit of concern that it’d go wrong, I put some heatproof tape on the CPU’s socket and got to work with the heat gun.</p>
<p>To my surprise, I removed the oscillator quite easily. I figured I may as well also remove the FT230X - and this also went far better than I anticipated. Well enough, in fact, that I soldered the removed IC onto a TSSOP-16 breakout board. I replicated the CPU board’s USB circuitry fairly closely on a breadboard, then plugged it in.</p>
<figure>
<img src="/images/trs20/enumerated.png" alt="" /><figcaption>wat.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>The chip is (I think) fine. I can dump its ROM, and I can make an LED flicker by sending to it using the virtual COM port driver.</p>
<p>So I rechecked the CPU board. I checked all the connections into the CPU, which are the only parts I didn’t replicate on the breadboard. I checked all the passives, in case I had a dud resistor or capacitor. Everything looked fine - so, not having much to lose here, I desoldered the poor IC from the breakout board and resoldered it to the CPU board.</p>
<figure>
<img src="/images/trs20/whereswally.png" alt="" /><figcaption>I admit I felt a little glum.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Well, that’s it. I can’t communicate with the CPU, I can’t see if it’s working, I’ve no idea what I could possibly do. I am unwilling to risk the price of another board assembly when there’s no apparent reason for failure.</p>
<p>I packed everything away, and nearly didn’t even write this post.</p>
<h2 id="the-next-day">The next day</h2>
<p>The only substantive difference between the breadboard setup and the CPU board setup is my admittedly less than perfect USB socket. So after <del>sulking</del>sleeping on it I tried measuring voltage levels on the breadboard vs. on the CPU board. I ran the USB socket without the main USB power applied to the board: this <em>in theory</em> is perfectly fine, as the FT230X tolerances are absolute, not expressed in terms of its supply voltage. But what I noticed was that VBUS was running at 2V, and D- at -0.5V, relative to ground supplied via the data USB. I checked an unconnected USB socket and got 5V and 0V respectively, with D+ at 3.3V. Hmm.</p>
<p>I reconnected the supply power for the CPU board, and re-measured. Now I saw 5V, 3.3V, and 0V for VBus, D+, and D-, which seemed right. At a loss, I tried one last thing:</p>
<figure>
<img src="/images/trs20/enumerated.png" alt="" /><figcaption>Why do you taunt me so?</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>It was enumerating again.</p>
<p>This should feel like a victory, but in truth it does not. I don’t know why it didn’t work, I don’t know why it started working, I don’t know whether it will stop working again in the future. But I ordered a replacement oscillator, and may as well press on.</p>
<figure>
<img src="/images/trs20/assembled%20board.jpg" alt="" /><figcaption>The fully assembled board.</figcaption>
</figure>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>The TRS-20 - ROM programming</title>
    <link href="https://bje.id.au/blog/posts/trs20/013-program-roms.html" />
    <id>https://bje.id.au/blog/posts/trs20/013-program-roms.html</id>
    <published>2020-07-10T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-07-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="/posts/trs20/012-build-it.html">last post</a> left off after soldering on the FPGA and its companion parts: the SPI Flash ROM, the 100MHz oscillator, all the power parts, and the programmable LEDs. The only way to know if it’s been designed properly and attached to the board without error is to have it do something observable, like control the LEDs. And the only way to do that is to program the SPI ROM.</p>
<p>The easy way is to order a ROM programmer that can handle SPI Flash ROMs (and, preferably, also handle the parallel ROM). But what would I learn from that?</p>
<!--more-->
<p>Instead, let’s use my STM32 “black pill” board as a programmer, using the USB serial interface to control it. The STM32 is a 3.3v board with an on-die SPI controller - with only one hitch. My black pill no longer powers up. I’ve no idea why, it seems to be failing to get power through the USB C socket, but there’s nothing wrong by a visual inspection.</p>
<p>Oh well.</p>
<p>The idea works well enough for me that I don’t want to just leave it there. Instead, I’m replacing my black pill board with a Nucleo-64, specifically the NUCLEO-F411RE. This is a slightly improved IC compared to the black pill’s STM32F401CC, and the Nucleo board is likely to be a higher quality product than a $6 part from an anonymous manufacturer. The Nucleo-64 board format has enough pins for me to directly program the parallel ROM without using shift registers.</p>
<h1 id="spi-flash-wiring">SPI Flash wiring</h1>
<p>Pin selection for the SPI ROM is a little fiddly, as STM32CubeMX presents me with an image of the IC’s pins, but I care about the board’s layout. The ’F411 has five SPI peripherals, and each peripheral has a few options for pins; after not too much time I’d selected SPI3 using pins PC10, 11, and 12 for SCK, MISO, and MOSI respectively. These pins are all grouped together on a pair of pin headers on one side of the board, close enough to the power pins that a <a href="https://docs.wemos.cc/en/latest/d1_mini_shiled/protoboard.html">D1 protoshield board</a> with a 2x8 female header can cover GND, 3V3, the three SPI pins, and an arbitrary pin (PD2) for slave select.</p>
<p>The circuit on the protoshield is trivial - a pull-up for /CS and a socket for the ROM - and you can see my handiwork in the image at the top of the post.</p>
<p>I won’t go into detail on the code work involved. I wrote a simple <a href="https://github.com/codebje/romble/blob/master/Src/flashrom.c">interface</a> for the Flash ROM, and implemented a <a href="https://github.com/codebje/romble/blob/master/Src/ymodem.c">YModem</a> receiver so I could upload over the ST-LINK’s USB serial port.</p>
<p>I burned on a simple image that just sets one LED to be always off, and binds the other to the 100MHz oscillator’s input via a 26-bit counter. This is around a 1.5Hz blink - if it works.</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb1"><pre class="sourceCode verilog"><code class="sourceCode verilog"><span id="cb1-1"><a href="#cb1-1"></a><span class="kw">module</span> poc(CLK1, LED1, LED2);</span>
<span id="cb1-2"><a href="#cb1-2"></a></span>
<span id="cb1-3"><a href="#cb1-3"></a>    <span class="dt">input</span> CLK1;</span>
<span id="cb1-4"><a href="#cb1-4"></a>    <span class="dt">output</span>              LED1, LED2;</span>
<span id="cb1-5"><a href="#cb1-5"></a></span>
<span id="cb1-6"><a href="#cb1-6"></a>    <span class="kw">assign</span> LED1 = <span class="dv">0</span>;</span>
<span id="cb1-7"><a href="#cb1-7"></a></span>
<span id="cb1-8"><a href="#cb1-8"></a>    <span class="dt">reg</span> [<span class="dv">25</span>:<span class="dv">0</span>]          counter;</span>
<span id="cb1-9"><a href="#cb1-9"></a>    <span class="dt">reg</span>                 toggle;</span>
<span id="cb1-10"><a href="#cb1-10"></a></span>
<span id="cb1-11"><a href="#cb1-11"></a>    <span class="kw">always</span> @(<span class="kw">posedge</span> CLK1)</span>
<span id="cb1-12"><a href="#cb1-12"></a>        counter &lt;= counter + <span class="bn">1&#39;b1</span>;</span>
<span id="cb1-13"><a href="#cb1-13"></a></span>
<span id="cb1-14"><a href="#cb1-14"></a>    <span class="kw">assign</span> LED2 = counter[<span class="dv">25</span>];</span>
<span id="cb1-15"><a href="#cb1-15"></a></span>
<span id="cb1-16"><a href="#cb1-16"></a><span class="kw">endmodule</span></span></code></pre></div>
<p>While I was at it, I figured I may as well make two images like this, one with <code>assign LED1 = 0;</code> and the other with <code>assign LED1 = 1;</code>. <a href="http://bygone.clairexen.net/icestorm/">Project IceStorm</a> supports multi-image bitstreams, so I can exercise my boot selector jumpers as well.</p>
<p>After straightening the ROM’s pins back out (use a removal tool: flat tweezers are excellent, fingers are not) and plugging it into the main board, well:</p>
<video controls="true" autoplay="true" loop="true" style="width: 100%">
<source type="video/mp4" src="/images/trs20/blinky-led.mp4">
</video>
<p>I stared at a blinking light for a somewhat absurd amount of time. The FPGA works. The oscillator works. The ROM works. The power works. Job more or less done!</p>
<h1 id="the-parallel-rom">The parallel ROM</h1>
<p>I thought about how I might want to do this. A neat job would be female headers on a board for the Nucleo to plug into, programming the ROM IC in a PLCC socket beside it. I could add a DIP8 socket and have a programmer for both ROMs in short order. But this is a lot of jumper wires to mess about with, and frankly I’m not really keen on it. So - pretty much every jumper lead I have is now in Frankenprogrammer.</p>
<figure>
<img src="/images/trs20/plcc-programmer.jpg" alt="" /><figcaption>So much better than a TL866II, right?</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>I hope to minimise my programming cycles - I need to work out how I can verify the whole CPU board is good, then work on producing enough of a ROM that I can boot up to something that’ll program other parts of the ROM over USB. PLCC sockets are only good for a few tens of insertions, so I want to be bootstrapped on-board ASAP.</p>
<p>Next up: completing the CPU board assembly.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>The TRS-20 - Assembling the board</title>
    <link href="https://bje.id.au/blog/posts/trs20/012-build-it.html" />
    <id>https://bje.id.au/blog/posts/trs20/012-build-it.html</id>
    <published>2020-06-26T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-06-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have all my parts, I have my boards, it’s time to assemble this thing. I’ll be starting with the highest risk components first, on the grounds that if I muck up I will have less to replace to try again.</p>
<!--more-->
<h2 id="soldering-round-one">Soldering, round one</h2>
<p>I’ve attempted the iCE40 IC first, as the most likely to fail. And indeed, it hasn’t gone at all well. There were terrible solder bridges on two sides, and while I’ve eventually figured out the technique for dealing with these I’ve applied substantial heat to get there. The board looks in good nick, perhaps due to the two large inner copper planes wicking heat away, but there’s a persistent short from 3.3V to GND that, obviously, is a deal-breaker. I’ve tested the other four boards and they’re all short-free so it’s very likely this is a soldering issue. I found and removed another short on two address lines, and think everything else is clear (no test points - a board design issue), but I don’t even know which of the supply/ground pin pairs has the short. I fear it may have somehow happened beneath the IC where I can’t see it, or with excess heat down a ground via delaminating the board enough for solder to worm its way to a connection with the power layer. It may just be solder sitting sneakily behind some pins, but there’s only two supply pins that are adjacent and I’ve inspected the everloving out of them both.</p>
<figure>
<img src="/images/trs20/dodgy-solder.png" alt="" /><figcaption>That big one on the left I’ve nicknamed ‘The Bridge of Sighs’.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>I’ve ordered three more FPGAs, and I’ll try again, armed perhaps with a greater fear of excessive solder paste, a new multimeter that doesn’t have one lead replaced by an alligator clip holding a screw, and my improved techniques for fixing small bridges. They won’t arrive until the end of the week, so I’ve put board assembly aside for now.</p>
<h2 id="programming-roms">Programming ROMs</h2>
<p>I have two ROMs to program: the bitstream to configure the FPGA (assuming I ever get it soldered on safely) and the boot/BIOS ROM. The bitstream ROM is programmed over SPI, and is a DIP-8 in a socket. I’m fairly confident I can solder up something to program bitstreams using my STM32F401 black pill board. The boot/BIOS ROM is a bit more difficult, as it’s a parallel device with 18 address pins, 8 data pins, and a little assortment of control pins. I’ll need shift registers to handle this. Luckily I have a little pile of 74HC595s lying around unused. Two of those gives me 16 of my 18 address pins at the cost of two µC pins, and two more for A<sub>16</sub> and A<sub>17</sub>. I can wire up the µC directly to the data pins, and to /OE and /WR, and I’ve only used 14 pins.</p>
<p>I will load up a perfboard with sockets, and then have to figure out how to have the STM32 read a programming bytestream over USB serial. But this can wait while I perform main board assembly - I don’t need more parts, just more time.</p>
<p>I’m also slowly working on a TRS-20 emulator, so I can crack on with writing a boot ROM that’s got a halfway decent chance of actually running on the real deal.</p>
<h2 id="soldering-round-two">Soldering, round two</h2>
<p>My replacement FPGAs arrived earlier than expected. I got in plenty of practice on the first board for dealing with 0.5mm pitch pins using an iron and absurd amounts of flux, so I thought I’d try drag soldering one. Now I have two badly soldered FPGAs on two boards. I don’t really think it’s worth trying to fix the second IC it’s that bad, and the first has been subject to so much heating and cooling and <em>still</em> has a sneakily hidden bridge somewhere between 3V3 and GND.</p>
<p>I tried a third FPGA on a fresh board. I have one spare FPGA and two spare boards. This time, I carefully lined up the IC then used a toothpick to put as little solder paste on as I could, then cracked in with the heat gun. There were a few bridges left, but this time I was able to get in and clean them up without using crazy heating cycles. I’ve checked all 100 pins to confirm they’re connected to what they should be, and not to what they shouldn’t be, and it’s all looking good.</p>
<p>So I got stuck into getting a few more components on the board. I have <em>absolutely no idea</em> if my 100MHz oscillator is on right. It’s a tiny QFN - the only no-lead part on the board - and I can see that at least two pads are soldered, the others <em>probably</em> are, and maybe it doesn’t have bridges, or heat damage from the hot air gun. I can’t really test it, and I didn’t have any particular use for it.</p>
<figure>
<img src="/images/trs20/power-components.png" alt="" /><figcaption>100 0.5mm pitch pins soldered neatly - and a handful of capacitors on crazy angles.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>The 1.2V regulator is a DDPAK, an absolutely enormous beast of a part. It features a large tab for heat transfer, and again I can’t see underneath it to know if solder paste melted or not. The DDPAK is designed to dissipate heat, so it fights every step of the way when soldering. Even the three pins wick heat magically away into the large copper pours and are difficult to solder. It’s on - but the tab might not be soldered down as well as it should be.</p>
<p>I am filled with regrets about choosing to use 0603 bypass capacitors, they’re fiddly. I’ve put on a half dozen or so, plus a few larger capacitors around the power management. My goal is to get enough soldered on to verify the power circuitry, and then to verify the FPGA is on safely, so I’ve done the DDPAK, the eFuse, and capacitors. I’ve yet to do the resistors, diode, and the R-78 3.3V regulator, more caps, and perhaps the MIC803.</p>
<p>That’s all for another day.</p>
<h2 id="soldering-round-three">Soldering, round three</h2>
<p>It is another day. I’ve pressed on, popping on a stack of resistors for the LEDs, eventual I2C bus pull-ups, CDONE pull-up, and power management resistors. I’ve finished off all the capacitors for the regulators, the FPGA, and its ROM. I’ve added the ROM’s socket, and an unprogrammed ROM is sitting in it, tempting fate. I’ve also added the power USB port, which in hindsight I should have done before the whopping great big capacitor that made access to the USB pins much harder than I’d have liked. All of it went pretty well, I only lost one 0603 resistor (and found it again when cleaning up, amazingly), most of my parts aren’t on <em>too</em> crooked, and there’s no shorts or, as far as I can determine, bad joints.</p>
<p>And finally, I added one LED, the power indicator LED. This is my first SMD LED, and finding the polarity of these parts proved a little harder than I’d expected. The data sheet said the underside would indicate the cathode with a single horizontal line, but the actual underside had a turnstile symbol instead. I wound up relying on the advice in the sheet that the anode is closest to the holes on the tape.</p>
<p>It is time to apply power. If I’ve done anything wrong in design or assembly, magic smoke will now escape.</p>
<h2 id="powering-up-round-one">Powering up, round one</h2>
<p>I pushed the USB cable into the socket, fearing the worst, hoping for the best. Today, I got the best: the power LED lit up. The board has juice! This LED is wired straight to the USB power supply, so it tells me that I don’t have a critical short somewhere, and that I do have a successfully soldered USB port, resistor, and correctly oriented LED. That’s quite a moment, but not the end of the story, not just yet.</p>
<figure>
<img src="/images/trs20/power-on.jpg" alt="" /><figcaption>Just an LED - and an important milestone.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>I have two regulators and a voltage divider network in my power circuitry. The RECOM should be converting the 5V supply from USB via the eFuse into 3.3V, while the DDPAK linear regulator supplies 1.2V from the same source. I gave them both a probe with the multimeter, and to my delight, both are showing the expected levels. The voltage divider for the MIC2774 reset controller is also performing properly, delivering 315mV to the 300mV comparator input. Nothing is unduly warm, so I feel confident in declaring my power circuitry design and assembly a success.</p>
<p>I have no idea just yet whether the FPGA, ROM, and 100MHz oscillator are in a good place. Tomorrow’s soldering task will be to add the remaining LEDs (including the two USR LEDs wired to the FPGA), the MIC803 supervisor, and the pull-up for the ROM’s Slave Select that I missed - U20 and R13 in the above image. After that I’ll choose between testing the FPGA out before committing RAM, ROM, and CPU, or pressing on with the actual computer part of this circuit.</p>
<p>The ROM programmers are becoming more important with every additional blob of solder hitting the board.</p>
<h2 id="soldering-round-four">Soldering, round four</h2>
<p>This time I’m methodically placing capacitors and resistors, aiming to complete all of each particular size. I’ve knocked out the 0.1µFs, although one is dangerously close to forming a bridge and needs fixing. I’ve put on all the 10kΩ and 2.2kΩ resistors - including deciding that I would use 10kΩ for the /INTx pull-ups instead of 2.2kΩ. I’ve finished all the LEDs off, five are the yellow-green diffuse diodes and three are green low-current clear. The clear LEDs have a dome on top which makes them a little fiddly to hold in place for hand soldering, but didn’t give too much trouble. I also put in the MIC803, which I realised I’d made harder for myself by soldering the SPI Flash socket in place first. There wasn’t much room to get in and heat it up, and it took a few goes to ensure the pin near the socket was adequately wetted.</p>
<p>I put on the 10kΩ resistor R12, which forms part of the voltage divider for VBUS sense on the FT230X USB chip. Since the FT230X isn’t currently programmed for VBUS sense, this means I’ve wired up an output chip with a resistor into GND, and this will draw 0.33mA current when that output is HIGH. I need to be careful not to solder on R11 until I’ve programmed the IC.</p>
<p>Foolishly, I also soldered on the PLCC-32 socket. Progress is barely visible after doing a few tens of 0603 parts, so I wanted some big visible progress in place. However, this is now going to get in the way for soldering the ICs close to the socket: U1 and U30 are SOIC8 ICs with one side of pins each about 7mm away from the socket. They’re handsolder pads, at least, so it should be okay, but I need to take the lesson to heart and not rush in to the big parts until I’ve dealt with the parts needing easier access.</p>
<p>Sadly, on power-up my LEDs didn’t light up as expected. 5V is still lighted, which is good news, but 3V didn’t light up while both USR LEDs wired to the FPGA did, albeit not as bright as the others. Since my understanding of the FPGA is that every IO pin goes Hi-Z during configuration, this seems like terrible news - if power is coming through that IC might be on the fritz. I re-read the iCE40 Programming and Configuration Guide, which does definitely say those pins are Hi-Z with pull-ups. The iCE40 family data sheet says both that I/O pins default to weak pull-down and weak pull-up, depending on which part of the sheet you’re at, but clearly these two pins at least are not wired to GND. There are 2.2kΩ resistors on those LEDs already, so for them to be visibly lit up the weak pull-up resistors can’t be that weak - or the FPGA might still be on the fritz.</p>
<p>The 3V LED was nothing more serious than a bad solder joint on one side, easily fixed.</p>
<p>At this point I’m confident that everything on the board so far has been soldered on correctly (if not necessarily neatly) but I have some doubts about whether the FPGA is still good, or if it’s been fried by clumsy handling or soldering. My next work is therefore going to focus on programming the SPI Flash ROM with a bitstream that can demonstrate the FPGA is good.</p>
<h2 id="errata">Errata</h2>
<ul>
<li>U7 has four floating pins that will become inputs if /BUSACK is active, and four pins that will be outputs wired directly into ground. I can perhaps fix it by also wiring the floating pins to ground - without doing that, using /BUSRQ might result in a short through the ’245 buffer.</li>
<li>There’s no solder mask between the pins of most of my SMD ICs. It’s not a critical failure by itself, but it significantly increases the risk of solder bridges. This may have contributed to my difficulty with the iCE40, and may cause problems for the 0.65mm pitch ICs I have yet to do.</li>
<li>The reset button. I didn’t check pins on this part, and they’re wrong. When the button is soldered on the reset input on the supervisor is always pulled low. I may try to jury rig something down the line, but for now I will just go without.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="potential-improvements">Potential improvements</h2>
<ul>
<li>Yanking a USB cable in and out for power is not great. I considered a power toggle switch, but chose to omit it - I think putting one in would be a substantial improvement.</li>
<li>The FPGA’s default pin state includes pull-ups; the USR LEDs are on at boot, until configuration is complete. Inverting these LEDs to be wired to +3.3V with an open drain pin configuration would prevent this.</li>
<li>The CBSEL jumpers could have been spaced 2.54mm apart and used a double row pin header, or perhaps DIP switches, though I wanted something with low chance of mechanical failure.</li>
<li>There’s a row of resistors for pull-ups that could have been replaced by two resistor arrays to take a bit less board real-estate up. Fixing U7’s floating and shorted pins will require resistor arrays to fit without major board layout changes.</li>
<li>The 100MHz oscillator in a QFN package is difficult, as I expected it would be. It’s also more important than I counted on, as it’s the only available clock for the FPGA without the processor’s PHI output. Using a bigger package for this oscillator would be a good change.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="budget-summary">Budget summary</h2>
<p>The budget is blown. I bought three more iCE40HX1Ks to cope with my first failure at soldering, I forgot I needed PLCC-32 sockets, and for the ROM programmer I’ve also had to buy replacements for failed parts. I’ll track my total spend and when I’ve either succeeded or admitted defeat on the CPU board I’ll tally the cost in parts for just the board, but I will no longer pretend I’m going to build a retrocomputer for $400.</p>
<table style="width:65%;">
<caption>Project status update</caption>
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 8%" />
<col style="width: 10%" />
<col style="width: 13%" />
<col style="width: 10%" />
<col style="width: 11%" />
<col style="width: 11%" />
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: center;">CPU</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Power</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Keyboard</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Video</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Memory</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Debug</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">███─</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">done</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">────</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">────</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">███─</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">done</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>The TRS-20 - CPU board design</title>
    <link href="https://bje.id.au/blog/posts/trs20/011-motherboard.html" />
    <id>https://bje.id.au/blog/posts/trs20/011-motherboard.html</id>
    <published>2020-06-06T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-06-06T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this post I’ll document my progress on the design of the CPU board. I’m still happy with the PC104 form factor, so into a 10cm² area I’ll see if I can pack on the socketed processor, a clock, the PC104 headers, a power supply, SRAM, and ROM. Snuck in around this needs to be the address decoding logic, glue logic, and a few status LEDs.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>I’ve also switched from Eagle CAD to KiCad for this stage of the project. The main motivation is frugality: I want to design a schematic of moderate complexity, which means multiple schematic files are desirable, but that feature is not part of the free edition of Eagle. As a bonus: the 3D rendering feature of KiCad is pretty fun, and adding parts is easy enough that I’m spending more time hunting for 3D models of parts than worrying about finding footprints or schematics.</p>
<h2 id="the-boards-main-features">The board’s main features</h2>
<p>The motherboard will be responsible for the core of the computer, with everything required for program execution natively on-board. It’s practically a single-board computer, though as seems to be the pattern for Z80-based SBCs there will be at most serial I/O on board, and that only if space permits.</p>
<p>The chief elements to fit on the board, in decreasing order of priority, are:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><a href="#cpu">The CPU</a></p>
<p>Without this, there’s no computer. Because the days of 5V are waning, I’ve decided to settle on a Z8L180-20 part at 3.3V. Whether I use a socketed part or risk a QFP-80 is still to be determined.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="#clock">The clock system</a></p>
<p>This needs to be close to the CPU. An 18.432MHz MEMS oscillator will have excellent rise and fall times, take up little room, and provide a USART compatible clock.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="#power">The power and reset supervision circuitry</a></p>
<p>The CPU needs to be held in reset long enough to initialise, and the single-IC solutions for this problem will also debounce my reset switch for me. This can’t reasonably be off-board, the CPU needs it to start.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="#memory">SRAM</a></p>
<p>Like the clock, this also needs to be close to the CPU for zero wait state access. There’s little choice other than a TSOP-II 48 pin part here.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="#power">Power regulation</a></p>
<p>While I could offload power regulation in a pinch I’d prefer to keep it on-board. I’ll feed in a Raspberry Pi 2.5A 5.1v Micro-USB supply and regulate that down to 3.3v and 1.2v on-board.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="#memory">Flash ROM</a></p>
<p>This could move off-board if necessary, but since it’s essential for booting I’d prefer not to. The tricky part for the ROM is how to program it. A boot loader in the ROM allowing it to be programmed via the Z180 has appeal but risks bricking my system, so this part needs to be socketed.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="#pic">Interrupt controller</a></p>
<p>Responding to interrupts requires programmable I/O registers. I’ve looked at a few ways to do this, and in the end I’ve settled on an ICE40HX1K FPGA, which should offer me plenty of flexibility to do other things as I think of them too, <em>if</em> I can get it in-system programmable. Running it as an I2C controller, for example, would be an interesting use of a few pins on the main header.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="#uart">Serial I/O</a></p>
<p>Without some kind of I/O I really won’t have a clue if my system is working. Ensuring I keep room for USART headers lets me communicate with the CPU after some amount of ROM wrangling, and get into a faster iteration on system development than I would otherwise have.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>This is a lot to try and pack onto a 10cm<sup>2</sup> board. I had originally planned to stick to two layers, but that makes routing substantially harder and I’ve caved and spent extra on four layers. I can offload some parts to a second board, with the caveat that signals will need to go across the PC104 headers. There’s no value I can see in aiming for PC104 pin compatibility, but even so my header pin count isn’t infinite.</p>
<h2 id="cpu">The CPU</h2>
<p>I’ve been aiming at the Z80180 family basically since I discovered the chip - the Z80 core plus a handful of useful peripherals. My debug IC is a rather vanilla Z80180-10 from Aliexpress clocked at 1MHz, with my eye set on (of course) the maximum speed of a Z8S180 clocked at 33MHz.</p>
<p>Running through the timing exercise of the last blog post, plus part selections while designing this board, have brought me to two accommodations. The first is that a 3.3V part has better compatibility with other parts I want to use, as mentioned above. The second is that while it’s possible for me to meet the 30ns timing constrants of a 33MHz part, doing so will require much more care and time. I’m nearly half way through the year and don’t even have a CPU board yet, so ensuring my ambitions don’t exceed my capabilities is important.</p>
<p>Also since the last blog post, all suppliers of the Z8L180 have dried up, unless I want to buy 100 of them. Which I do not. However, if I am reading the datasheet correctly, the Z8S180 will happily run at 3.3V as long as it’s not clocked over 20MHz. Back to the S180 it is.</p>
<p>Parts required:</p>
<ul>
<li>Z8S180-33 CPU</li>
<li>PLCC socket</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="clock">Clocking in</h2>
<p>The Z80180 needs to be clocked at a <a href="003-basic-board.html">magic frequency</a> for UART usage, though the S180 adds a baud rate generator that can divide the clock by a 16-bit value. I toyed with the idea of having a software configurable clock, mostly so I could clock up to maximum for general use and clock down to something approaching the TRS-80 Model I’s 1.777MHz for an emulation mode (10.664MHz crystal divided by 6). But the Z180 is not a Z80. It won’t ever execute a Z80 program at the same speed as an original Z80. I’d rather save a lot of board space and hassle and use a fixed clock that gets my Z180 up and running, at the cost of definitely not being able to run original TRS-80 software at the original speed.</p>
<p>Parts required:</p>
<ul>
<li>A MEMS oscillator at 18.432MHz</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="power">Power supply</h2>
<p>Much like clocks, I’ve cycled around a few ideas here. I need a rough estimate of the total power my system will draw, which I’ve guessed at under an amp. I need input power from an AC adapter, and regulated 3.3V and 1.2V supplies on board. And I don’t want it all to take up too much space, else I’ll have to put it on a separate board.</p>
<p>My solution currently (sic!) is to use a Raspberry Pi USB-Micro power supply. These supplies are rated for 2.5A and deliver power into a USB Micro port. There’s no power negotiation involved - on the Pi the data pins are unconnected - so there’s no IC needed. The supply should deliver a fairly well regulated 5.1V that I can down-regulate to 3.3V and 1.2V.</p>
<p>A RECOM R-783.3-1.0 DC/DC converter is pretty much ideal for me. It’s a three-pin potted package containing all the components needed to regulate 4.75V to 18V down to 3.3V, at 1A. All I need to add is a bypass capacitor or two, and to provide ~250mA at 1.2v for the FPGA’s core with a simple LDO like the <a href="http://ww1.microchip.com/downloads/en/DeviceDoc/22070a.pdf">MCP1824S</a>.</p>
<p>Power management comes in the form of a small collection of ICs. The <a href="http://www.ti.com/lit/ds/symlink/tps25921l.pdf?ts=1588770951061">TPS25921</a> eFuse protects the computer from over-current faults. A 150kΩ resistor sets the current limit of the eFuse to 1.6A. An eFuse provides similar protections to a traditional fuse, but with a much faster response rate. The <a href="http://ww1.microchip.com/downloads/en/DeviceDoc/mic2774.pdf">MIC2774</a> reset controller monitors two voltages and maintains a reset signal for 140ms to 280ms after voltages have reached their target levels, while also supporting a manual reset input.</p>
<p>To let me know what’s going on, I’ll want an LED on the 5.1V supply, an LED tied to the /FLT line of the TPS25921, and an LED on the output of the RECOM. The MIC2774 has a very low current tolerance on its /MR line, so I’ll need to find some other way to indicate that the CPU is being released from reset. I’ve chosen a mix of orange and yellow-green LEDs, which all have a 1.9-2.4V forward voltage and a 30mA forward current. These will need resistors for both 5V and 3.3V, at around 20mA.</p>
<p>Parts required:</p>
<ul>
<li>USB micro port, 2A capable</li>
<li>RECOM R-783.3-1.0 DC/DC converter</li>
<li>1x 22uF MLCC capacitor, 1210</li>
<li>1x 10uF MLCC capacitor, 1206</li>
<li>2x 1uF MLCC capacitor, 0805</li>
<li>TPS25921L, 8SOIC</li>
<li>150kΩ resistor, 0603</li>
<li>MIC2774, SOT23-5</li>
<li>270kΩ, 732kΩ resistors, 0603</li>
<li>Orange and yellow-green LEDs</li>
<li>68Ω and 150Ω resistors, 0603</li>
</ul>
<p>And in general for power management:</p>
<ul>
<li>Lots of 0.1uF MLCC capacitors, 0603</li>
<li>Lots of 10kΩ resistors, 0603</li>
</ul>
<figure>
<img src="/images/trs20/power%20supply.svg" alt="" /><figcaption>A higher part count than I would have liked in the end, but still relatively simple.</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="memory">RAM and ROM</h2>
<p>The <a href="010-timing-check.html">last post</a> went into detail on the specific timings required for zero wait state memory access. In particular, zero wait state ROM requires clever tricks with enabling the IC before I am even sure that a memory request is coming. In the end I’ve chosen not to be too clever, and instead require at least one wait state for memory accesses when the ROM (or off-board memory-mapped I/O) is in use.</p>
<h3 id="utilising-the-z180-mmu">Utilising the Z180 MMU</h3>
<p>One of the selling points for the Z180 is the onboard peripherals, pegged as space and cost savers. The peripheral of the most interest to me right now is the memory management unit. This maps the 20-bit physical address space of the Z180 to a 16-bit logical space, neatly sidestepping a number of problems I’d otherwise face.</p>
<p>The Z180’s MMU divides logical memory into three regions. At the bottom and top of memory are what the processor designers call the Common Areas, and between them is the Bank Area. Common Area 0 at logical address <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="bn">$0000</span></code> is always mapped to physical address <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="bn">$00000</span></code>, and at boot is 64K in size. The Bank Area starts at the end of Common Area 0, and Common Area 1 starts at the end of the Bank Area. All addresses are aligned to 4K, such that logical addresses are 4-bits long and physical addresses are 8-bits long.</p>
<p><img src="/images/z180-mmu.svg" /></p>
<p>At reset, the Z180 will set the program counter to <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="bn">$0000</span></code> and will fetch an opcode from phyiscal address <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="bn">$00000</span></code>. Putting the ROM at this physical address makes booting simple, but after boot it makes Common Area 0 less valuable, as it must always be the boot ROM. CP/M in particular expects useful memory at least as low as <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="bn">$0200</span></code>.</p>
<p>More annoying is that dividing a 1Mb physical memory space into one 512Kb and two 256Kb regions is really easy with an <a href="http://www.ti.com/lit/gpn/sn74lvc1g29">SN74LVC1G29</a> - but its truth table only aligns with selecting SRAM when A<sub>19</sub> is low, and using A<sub>18</sub> to choose between the off-board bus or the ROM when A<sub>19</sub> is high. With a 5.1ns propagation delay this IC is plenty fast enough for the job.</p>
<table>
<caption>How RAM, ROM, and the BUS relate to the CPU’s signals</caption>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>A<sub>19</sub></th>
<th>A<sub>18</sub></th>
<th>RAM</th>
<th>BUS</th>
<th>ROM</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>L</td>
<td>-</td>
<td>L</td>
<td>H</td>
<td>H</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>H</td>
<td>L</td>
<td>H</td>
<td>L</td>
<td>H</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>H</td>
<td>H</td>
<td>H</td>
<td>H</td>
<td>L</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>But for this to work, I need to have SRAM at phyiscal address <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="bn">$00000</span></code>. Except right at boot.</p>
<h3 id="booting-from-rom">Booting from ROM</h3>
<p>The /RESET signal on the CPU will be pulled low by the MIC2774 voltage supervisor for 140ms or so after power is first applied or the reset button is mashed. When this signal goes high the processor will enter its reset cycle and very shortly thereafter it will start the first opcode read cycle for address <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="bn">$00000</span></code>.</p>
<p>To instead read that first opcode from ROM at <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="bn">$80000</span></code> I need A<sub>19</sub> to be high after reset. I can OR together the output of a D flip-flip and A<sub>19</sub>, and latch the flip-flop high on the rising edge of /RESET. I also need to clear the flip-flop during the boot sequence. Feeding the inverted A<sub>19</sub> line into the /CLR line of the flip-flop will clear it when A<sub>19</sub> rises, which I can arrange to happen by programming the MMU and jumping.</p>
<object class="paper" data="/images/shadow-rom.svg" type="image/svg+xml">
</object>
<p>In this circuit, U4 is an SN74LVC1G29 2-of-3 decoder. Its A1 input selects its Y0 output when A1 is low. When A1 is high, it selects either Y1 or Y2 depending on whether A0 is low or high, respectively. Feeding into U4 is A<sub>19a</sub>, which is the output of U3, an OR gate. The idea is that a high BOOTUP signal means A<sub>19a</sub> is set no matter what the real A<sub>19</sub> does, and BOOTUP is active at boot.</p>
<p>To achieve this goal, BOOTUP is the Q output of a D flip flop (U1, SN74LVC1G74) whose D line is tied to V<sub>CC</sub>. With its clock signal coming from /RESET, the flip-flop latches Q high when /RESET has a rising edge, or when the CPU is coming out of reset. This in turn makes A<sub>19a</sub> high after reset, causing the CPU to address ROM instead of RAM.</p>
<p>To disable BOOTUP, any CPU access that has A<sub>19</sub> set will do. This feeds into the inverter U2 (SN74LVC1G04), which drives /CLR low on U1, resetting BOOTUP. In this way, all the ROM code needs to do is use the MMU to map ROM into the logical space, then jump to it, and RAM access will be enabled.</p>
<p>While /RESET is active, the address lines from the processor are high-Z. However, the Z8S180 has auto-latches on all its I/O pins, so A<sub>19</sub> will be pulled either low or high - due to its design, it will most likely be pulled high. A pull-down resistor will keep it low when it’s not being driven, and prevent my flip-flop from being reset incorrectly.Zilog’s AN0009 discusses choice of resistor strength, but the text has several errors that muddy the choice a little.</p>
<p>Alternatively, I can combine the signal from A<sub>19</sub> with the signal from /M1. /M1 is held high during reset, and will only go low for a small number of CPU modes, only one of which will occur during boot-up: fetching opcodes. Instead of using an inverter at U2 I can use another IC that will output low iff /M1 is low and A<sub>19</sub> is high. The logic function is a two-input OR (or NAND) gate with one inverted input, <code>/M1 | ~A19</code>. The SN74LVC1G57 and ’97 both support this configuration in a SOT-23-6 package.</p>
<p>I will also swap out the 1G74 for a 1G175 which has no /Q and no /PRE, also in a SOT23-6 package. Dropping the unnecessary pins saves some board space.</p>
<h3 id="programming-the-rom">Programming the ROM</h3>
<p>Until reaching this section, the /WE input of my ROM was hard-wired to Vcc, and I planned to laboriously remove the thing from its socket, put it in a programming socket, burn a new image on, and move it back. Well, no more! I sat down and had a proper read of the datasheet, and I’ve convinced myself that programming it via the CPU is no harder than ensuring I have a wait state or two configured and just writing bytes to the right memory addresses. To write one byte, you need to write <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="bn">$AA</span></code> to <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="bn">$5555</span></code>, then <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="bn">$55</span></code> to <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="bn">$2AAA</span></code>, then <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="bn">$A0</span></code> to <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="bn">$5555</span></code>, and finally, write the byte to program to the address it should be at. Of course, this is Flash memory so you can only write zeros, and must also first erase a sector or the whole chip to one, but this too is accomplished with a sequence of bytes written to magic addresses.</p>
<p>I’ve wired /WE up to the memory write logic, and /WE will now go active when /MREQ and /WR go active. /CE will go active when A<sub>19</sub> (modified by the flip-flop) and /MREQ are active but A<sub>18</sub> is not. If I got it wrong, I only have one trace to cut to disable Flash writes altogether.</p>
<p>Other than needing a series of bytes written on the bus to write one byte to the Flash memory, there’s also of course a much larger time required to write that final byte. This time begins after /WE goes inactive, so the usual CPU write cycle will latch the byte in for writing. Completion of the write can be detected by simple timing, or by reading a byte and examining bit 7, which will be the complement of the true data until the write is finished, or bit 6, which will toggle high and low on successive reads until the write is finished.</p>
<h2 id="pic">Interrupt controller</h2>
<p>There are four interrupt lines on the Z180. The /NMI always restarts the processor at <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="bn">$0066</span></code>. /INT0 has three modes of operation. Mode 0 fetches a single byte instruction from the bus. Mode 1 restarts at fixed address <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="bn">$0033</span></code>. Mode 2 fetches an index into an interrupt vector from the bus, and is the mode I expect to use. /INT1 and /INT2 construct an address similarly to /INT0 Mode 2, but the index is retrieved from a register instead of the data bus. Internal interrupts operate in the same way as /INT1 and /INT2, and all such interrupts have a fixed 5-bit code specific to that interrupt source.</p>
<p>It’s common for Z80 machines to daisy-chain peripherals that raise interrupts. Each peripheral in the chain has an Interrupt Enable Input (IEI) pin. If this pin is asserted low, the peripheral must not signal an interrupt to the CPU. The highest priority peripheral has this pin tied to Vcc. Each peripheral also has an Interrupt Enable Output (IEO) pin that will be connected to the IEI of the next lowest priority peripheral. When the peripheral wishes to raise an interrupt it will assert IEO. If its IEI is not asserted, it will also assert the OR-wired /INT0 line. This will interrupt the processor, which will begin an interrupt acknowledge cycle. Only a peripheral with IEI unasserted will respond by writing its interrupt vector to the bus, then deasserting /INT. It will not deassert IEO until it sees the processor fetch a RETI instruction from the bus while the peripheral’s IEI line is deasserted.</p>
<p>A higher priority peripheral can interrupt another peripheral’s interrupt service routine. A lower priority peripheral must wait until all higher priority interrupts have been serviced before raising its own. And each peripheral must watch the bus for opcode fetch cycles, to detect RETI.</p>
<p>The scheme is quite neat, allowing a priority interrupt scheme without a dedicated controller. However, it’s not at all suited to a PC/104-style stack of boards, where every pin passes directly through each layer to the next. It’s not possible to have a daisy chained signal with stacked headers.</p>
<p>Since I’m not using any of the Z80 peripheral ICs, this isn’t a big problem. I can instead use an Intel 8259 style interrupt controller: one CPU interrupt line is split into a number of peripheral interrupt lines, each claimed by a single peripheral. This requires hard wiring peripherals to the appropriate interrupt on each child board, but doesn’t need any specific wiring for interrupt acknowledgement. Typically a peripheral will keep its interrupt flag active until acknowledged directly via I/O operations, or will keep it active for a short period.</p>
<p>The FPGA is also able to run an I2C core, and maybe down the track other tricks, so I’ve used five pins for interrupts and two for SDA/SCL lines. The I2C lines need pull-ups, and I’ve chosen 2.2kΩ. This is 1.5mA of current drain to pull low, but most of the time those lines will be idle.</p>
<p>The 8259A interface watches for rising edges or high signal levels on its interrupt lines, but I would prefer to configure the inputs in the FPGA as hi-Z unless explicitly configured as enabled rather than adding pull-downs or jumpers.</p>
<p>The FPGA itself requires an SPI slave device to feed it configuration data. I’ve chosen a DIP-8 package ROM in a socket so I can remove and reprogram it reasonably easily. The IC is a Winbond 32Mbit ROM, which has room for around 129 bitstream images for an iCE40HX1K device at 32,303 bytes per bitstream. The iCE40 has the option of selecting one of four image locations on boot based on the state of two pins at reset, or under software control using two internal signals. This allows me to store a bitstream in a different region of the Flash memory and load that image into the FPGA to test it before committing it to be the main boot-up bitstream. Adding a few jumpers to control the cold boot pins lets me have an emergency recovery bitstream I never touch.</p>
<figure>
<img src="/images/trs20/pcb_fpga.png" alt="" /><figcaption>The PCB’s layout is dominated by capacitors that are large enough for me to solder.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>The FPGA is a 0.5mm pitch VQFP-100 IC. This might be the most difficult part to solder on this board. I have done a practice solder of a TQFP-100, which sadly had several bridged pins. I corrected those bridges after buying the flux I should have used in the first place, but I’ve no idea if I cooked the IC with my hamfisted soldering and repair attempts. I’m a little nervous about this. Also in this section of the board is the only no-lead package I’ve used. X1 is a 100MHz MEMS oscillator that has no specific reason to exist, other than someday maybe I’d like a 100MHz clock input on the FPGA. Because it doesn’t need to be there, mucking X1 up won’t be such a big deal.</p>
<p>The FPGA is connected to all address and data lines, after buffering. It receives the CPU control signals: /MREQ, /IORQ, /RD, /WR, and /M1. It is the only part of the system wired up to the DMA control signals and the bus master control signals, and controls the three maskable external interrupt lines. It’s also wired to USART1’s RX and TX pins, and since taking the above image I also wired up CTS1. Again, I have no specific plans here, but it costs nothing except the time to try for a neat trace to leave the option of using USART1 with the FPGA open.</p>
<p>The control input lines for the CPU are all pulled high with 10kΩ resistors. Each pin on the iCE40HX1K has a drive current of 8mA maximum (“sysIO Single-Ended DC Electrical Characteristics”, iCE40 LP/HX Family Data Sheet) for an R<sub>min</sub> of 412.5Ω. R<sub>max</sub> is determined by timing constraints. For interrupts it’s not too critical. Sooner is better, but using 2.2kΩ at the ~15pF capacitance on the CPU and traces is around 30ns, and I will live with that. The /DREQn signals indicate to the CPU that an I/O device is ready for a DMA read or write to proceed, and it shouldn’t matter terribly if it’s delayed 30ns either.</p>
<p>/WAIT is a bit trickier. The Z8018x User Manual recommends synchronising changes to the signal with the rising edge of the system clock to meet timing requirements. This suggests a D flip-flop clocked from PHI sitting between open-drain drivers of /WAIT and the input pin on the CPU, with a pull-up to keep it high in the absence of a /WAIT claim. The ’175 D flip-flop I’m using elsewhere will do fine for this job: it has an input capacitance of around 3pF, so at 2.2kΩ this is close to a 10ns delay. With around 62ns to react and insert an additional wait state (assuming the CPU supplies at least one) this is a reasonable delay.</p>
<p>The two jumpers to configure <code>CBSEL0</code> and <code>CBSEL1</code> are below the ROM socket. U20 is a MIC803 supervisor, wired to <code>CRESET_B</code> on the FPGA. This pin pulls low to hard reset the FPGA, and the MIC803 holds it low for 20-44ms after the 3.3V rail has powered up. This is because the SPI ROM requirements include it being ready to accept commands 10µs after meeting power-on conditions, but the Winbond ROM takes a minimum of 20µs. The FPGA will be configured and ready to communicate long before the CPU has been released from reset with its minimum 140ms reset hold time - at the slowest configuration frequency, the typical configuration time is 53ms. This falls to 13ms with the fastest configuration frequency.</p>
<p>During this review, I found two errors in the PCB layout above. The first was the lack of a pull-up resistor on <code>CRESET_B</code>. Without this, the FPGA would have reset itself randomly as the MIC803 is an open-drain supervisor. The second is that I had a pull-up resistor on the SPI clock line, which the iCE40 does not want or recommend, and which the Winbond also doesn’t specify. I’ve added one and removed the other. I also noticed I haven’t connected <code>CDONE</code> to a status LED, which would at this point require rerouting large parts of the board to accommodate. It’s properly pulled up to Vcc as per the iCE40 programming manual, at least.</p>
<h2 id="uart">Serial I/O</h2>
<p>The Z180 has two USARTs, one with a full suite of control signals and one with just /CTS. I have wired USART1 up to the FPGA, which leaves USART0 as the obvious choice for my first interface into my computer. The easiest way to handle it is to expose a pin header with the various signals and use a USB to serial dongle to hook it up to a terminal program. Neater, though, is to put the USB port directly on the board and use one of many USB to UART ICs directly. I’ve chosen the FTDI FT230X, which can be powered at 3.3V without needing an external clock, can drive RX/TX LEDs, and has CTS/RTS signalling.</p>
<p><img src="/images/trs20/schm-usb-serial.svg" /></p>
<p>I’ve chosen to run the FT230X in a self powered configuration, using my on-board power to supply the IC. In this configuration there’s a few items to check off:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>It’s not nice to push current down the D wires to an inactive hub or host. To resolve this the FT230X expects to have a VBUS sense input on one of its four configurable I/O pins, which is just a voltage divider on VBUS from the USB port. When this input reads zero the FT230X isolates the D wires. When it’s high the FT230X pulls D+ up to 3.3V, which identifies the FT230X as a full speed device.</li>
<li>There is an internal LDO regulator that provdes 3.3V to various internal components. It also provides power output on the 3V3OUT pin which can be wired to VCCIO to supply power for the I/O pins. When VCC is less than 4.3V this voltage will fall out of regulation, and the FT230X datasheet says that when VCC is at 3.3V, 3V3OUT becomes an input pin and should be connected to VCC. Without this those internal components won’t get the 3.3V they need.</li>
<li>Some revisions of this IC had a fault in which they would mistakenly believe the host or hub had powered down, and USB communications would stop. This was fixed in revision D of the chip, which I believe was released in 2012 or so. The work-around for revisions A, B, and C is to pull a Keep Awake input low on another configurable I/O pin.</li>
</ol>
<p>These things aren’t as straightforward to resolve as I would like. For each item to check off, there’s a corresponding wrinkle to deal with.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>All four CBUSx pins are programmed as outputs in the factory. They can be reprogrammed easily over USB, but trying to connect over USB when CBUS0 is configured as an output and wired up to get ~3.4V from VBUS is a recipe for smoke. To sort this out, I need to avoid soldering R11 and R12 until I have reprogrammed the IC.</li>
<li>KiCad has a feature that treats having more than one power output on a net as an error. This is generally a good idea as it’ll pick up if you’ve accidentally wired two voltage sources together. However 3V3OUT is marked as a power output in the FT230X package, but it must be wired up to the 3.3V output of my regulator. KiCad complains about this. I could copy the FT230X package and modify the pin to be an input, but instead I am just going to live with KiCad telling me I have an error.</li>
<li>I expect I will get a revision D chip when ordering from a reputable supplier like DigiKey, but I can’t easily fix the problem once I’ve soldered the chip in place. I’ve added a resistor on the back of the board to pull CBUS3 to ground, which I can jumper or put a low value resistor on in the unlikely circumstance that my IC has this fault - after programming CBUS3 to the right function, that is.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="reviewing-everything">Reviewing everything</h2>
<p>The <a href="/images/trs20/cpu%20board.pdf">full schematic</a> shows how long this has taken me - I started work on this in February. It’s not quite complete yet, either - I want to review the datasheets of each IC and ensure the pin assignments are right, because it’s dang hard to fix that sort of problem once you’ve fabbed a board.</p>
<p>So here we go, one IC at a time, checking everything. Let’s see how many errors I pick up, and sweat over how many I don’t pick up.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>I have 1210, 1206, and 0805 capacitors in my DigiKey BOM for the 22uF, 10uF, and 1uF parts, respectively. On the board I’d assigned 0805 footprints to them all. I fixed that up, and popped a second 22uF on near the USB power input. The eFuse IC also suggests a Schottky diode on the output to protect against negative transients, which I am still considering.</li>
<li>I wired D+ to USBDM and D- to USBDP on the FT230X. You can see the mistake in the schematic above. I think it’s because they just lined up neatly that way. I needed to rotate the FT230X on the board to resolve it.</li>
<li>My 74LVC2G32 gates had the wrong pin assignments in the schematic. Rather than use the two-unit IC schematic supplied with KiCad I drew up my own one-unit schematic, and got it wrong. There’s three on the board, but they just needed re-routing.</li>
<li>My MCP1824S linear regulator was wired directly to the USB power, not to the eFuse output. On top of that, I’m not really happy with a 300mA limit for the FPGA’s core. I have no idea how much power it will actually draw, I can’t find that information, but other board designs I’ve looked at give it more juice. So - it’s now an MCP1826S rated for 1A, in a 3DDPAK footprint that can dissipate twice as much heat. If I can solder it down. DDPAKs are huge, so I had to move a few things around to fit it in. And I threw in that diode. I should be able to feed up to 700mA to the FPGA without any stress on the parts now.</li>
<li>A big one. I force A<sub>19</sub> high at boot to select ROM - but A<sub>18</sub> will be low, which would have selected unassigned bus memory addresses. I correctly identified the ROM would be at <code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span class="bn">$80000</span></code>, and clearly got that right in the circuit that forces A<sub>19</sub> high, but got it wrong in my logic table and wiring.</li>
<li>Another big one, courtesy BFLmouse from the 8 Bit World Discourse server: U16 is a ’245 buffer for the data bus, with DIRection controlled by /WR. If the CPU releases the bus via /BUSREQ, then this buffer must stay off the data bus. It needs the inverse of /BUSACK wired into /OE to disable the outputs. This could also be applied to the /OE pins of the address ’245s, but their DIR pin is wired to /BUSACK already - when /BUSACK is low, the Z180’s address lines are high-Z, and those ’245s will replicate whatever’s on the address bus outside to be ignored by the CPU on the inside.</li>
<li>KiCad’s SOT-23 footprints are smaller than the parts I’ve checked expect. I’ve switched to the hand soldering footprints in most cases, which gives me more room to get in with an iron and ensures I have enough overhang to successfully solder these parts down even if I’m not perfectly lined up. The same appears to be true of the diode footprints.</li>
<li>The lack of connection of the <code>CDONE</code> signal bothered me enough that I did the work to add an LED in. This meant moving a few components around to make room for an extra LED in the status LED section of the board. It also meant figuring out why the iCEstick appears to have an LED wired up to a 4.7kΩ resistor from 3.3V - at 1.8V<sub>F</sub> that’s only 0.32mA of forward current, though it’s also only 0.7mA of current into the <code>CDONE</code> pin when it’s being pulled low. I think the board must be using very low current LEDs, so I added a few of those to my BOM and I’ll drive them with 2.2kΩ resistors.</li>
<li>This isn’t really a board error, but I also added two user LEDs to the FPGA. This will let me do the usual “blinky” FPGA test code and confirm it’s working reasonably correctly early on, and let me use those LEDs as “printf debug” signals when programming the FPGA to interact with the CPU. And when it’s all working satisfactorily, I’ll have two system-controlled status lights.</li>
<li>The footprint for the MCP1826S didn’t match the datasheet in pretty much any dimension. I suspect it would have been okay, but I replaced it with a footprint that does match the datasheet. I also boosted the input capacitor to 4.7µF, which the datasheet seems to like sprinkling around a lot. The power input comes off a fairly long cable, so that extra buffering is likely to be used.</li>
<li>All CPU output signals were buffered before reaching the 40-pin header except for PHI. That now runs through a clock fanout buffer IC (the Microchip Technology PL133-37) with three outputs - one is used for the /WAIT flip-flop, one feeds both the FPGA and the header, and one is unused.</li>
</ol>
<p>I’ve checked all components wired to the address and data buses. I’ve checked every datasheet for pins, footprints, capacitor and resistor selection guidelines. I’ve reviewed whether component labels are obscured by other components or vias. And I’ve, most importantly, added decor to the board with the excellent <a href="https://www.1001fonts.com/park-tech-cg-font.html">Park Tech CG Font Family</a> and an adaptation of a logo Zilog was using in the ’80s and ’90s. The second revision schematic is <a href="/images/trs20/cpu%20board%20rev%202.pdf">here</a>.</p>
<p>This is a risky project for me. I’ve never designed such a complex circuit before, nor have I soldered so many tiny SMD parts. Most of the elements of this design are new to me: FPGAs, USB ICs, and management of the timing constraints the 18.432Mhz clock demands. This blog post serves as my major design review, and picked up a handful of issues that would have been painful to hit after fabrication.</p>
<p>I’ve pulled the trigger on ordering parts (they left Honolulu early this morning) and the board (four layers with ENIG finish, in fabrication) for close to $190 all up, so my budget is now blown. I’ve got to somehow successfully solder all the parts to the board, write code for the FPGA, write a ROM, and hopefully not discover any mistakes that I can’t monkey patch, and if all that goes to plan I’ll have a working computer I can interact with over a USB serial link. Adding keyboard and video I/O will have to wait.</p>
<p><img src="/images/trs20/logo.svg" /></p>
<table style="width:86%;">
<caption>Project status update</caption>
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 21%" />
<col style="width: 8%" />
<col style="width: 10%" />
<col style="width: 13%" />
<col style="width: 10%" />
<col style="width: 11%" />
<col style="width: 11%" />
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: center;">Budget</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">CPU</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Power</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Keyboard</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Video</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Memory</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Debug</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">$425.76 of $400</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">███─</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">███─</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">────</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">────</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">███─</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">done</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>The TRS-20 - Timing check</title>
    <link href="https://bje.id.au/blog/posts/trs20/010-timing-check.html" />
    <id>https://bje.id.au/blog/posts/trs20/010-timing-check.html</id>
    <published>2020-05-03T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-05-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am working on the CPU board design, which covers too many topics and decisions to fit into just one post. This particular post explores timing in depth, checking that I understand how fast my logic circuits must be to keep the bus contention free and the CPU state valid.</p>
<!--more-->
<h2 id="but-first-a-digression">But first, a digression…</h2>
<p>When, say, an adder circuit in a CPU is presented with some values on its input wires, some brief amount of time will elapse before the correct value presents on its output wires. In the meantime, it’s even possible that the output value will pass through intermediate states before settling on the right answer. The clock in a processor is the solution to this: it doesn’t matter what the circuit does while computing its answer, so long as it’s got the right answer by the time the next clock transition happens. The clock signal synchronises all the circuits of the processor, shuffling data from circuit to circuit with metronomic regularity.</p>
<p>When you pop out of the CPU and look at its immediate peripherals, the clock signal comes along for the ride. External components must march to the same drum as the processor, consuming data it outputs before the processor has moved on to the next task, and providing data as input before the processor acts on it.</p>
<p>This manifests in data sheets and other documentation as <em>timing diagrams</em>. These diagrams have time as the horizontal axis, and signal levels as the vertical axis, with multiple signals on the same diagram to show how the signals must synchronise with each other. If there’s a clock synchronising the signals, it’ll usually be the first signal in the diagram. Since the diagram’s purpose is to show relative timing constraints, the time axis isn’t accurate - if two signals change at the same point horizontally, they’re only specified to change at the same time if the diagram indicates a zero time delay between them.</p>
<figure>
<img src="/images/timing-diagram-example.svg" alt="" /><figcaption>Three signals (one a bus), and two indicated timing data.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>A timing diagram’s value is in explaining how one signal’s change in state is related to another signal. In the above diagram, a table would give an upper or lower bound for the intervals marked <code>1</code> and <code>2</code>. An upper bound for interval <code>1</code> would specify the maximum time that the address lines will settle after the rising edge of T1. A lower bound for interval <code>2</code> would specify the minimum time that the address lines will be settled before /MREQ falls.</p>
<h2 id="processor-timing-details-for-the-z180">Processor timing details for the Z180</h2>
<p>For the Z180 processor, there’s a feast of timing diagrams to dine on. They get their own section of the User Manual, and are one of the few pieces of information that appear in both the User Manual and the specification document. They’re accompanied by large data tables specifying bounds for various durations in the diagram. Time value t<sub>CYC</sub> is the clock cycle time - the time between each rising edge. For the Z8L180-20 t<sub>CYC</sub> lies between 50ns and DC, reflecting that the maximum speed of the processor is 20MHz (<span class="math inline">\(\frac{1}{20e^6} = 50e^{-9}\)</span>), and there is no minimum speed: you can stop its clock entirely.</p>
<p>Some of these timing values tell me useful information for my board design - my clock should be able to satisfy not only the clock cycle time bounds, but also the high and low pulse width bounds, which are only specified as minimum values. The Z80180 expects that the low and high pulses are each at least 40ns long. The upper bound is determined by the actual clock cycle time and the other pulse time minimum - for a 100ns cycle, the maximum high or low pulse is 60ns. There’s also clock rise and fall times: signal levels don’t change instantaneously, and if they transition too slowly a CMOS input can oscillate between reading a high and a low, or if you’re lucky, just chew up relatively huge amounts of power.</p>
<p>Others of these timing values tell me useful information for my component selection, when read in conjunction with a timing diagram. How fast does my SRAM have to be if I want to access it with no wait states? Well - in an opcode fetch cycle, the address pins will stabilise no more than t<sub>AD</sub> (30ns) after the first rising edge of the first clock cycle of the opcode fetch machine cycle, and no less than t<sub>AS</sub> (5ns) before /MREQ or /IORQ falls. In turn, /MREQ promises it will fall no later than t<sub>MED1</sub> (25ns) after the falling edge of that first clock cycle. Similarly, t<sub>RDD1</sub> (25ns) promises that /RD will fall at most that long after the falling edge as well. There’s nothing tying /RD and /MREQ together though, so there’s no commitment made as to which will fall first, or how much time will elapse between the two falling.</p>
<p>It’s all a bit complicated. Perhaps a diagram would help…</p>
<figure>
<img src="/images/z180-timing-main.png" alt="" /><figcaption>z8018x User Manual (UM005004-0918), p.197, Figure 81.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>There’s a lot going on in this one diagram, but I can use it to produce the information I really need - if I have 12ns SRAM, how fast does my glue logic have to be before I need a wait state? And for my Flash ROM and any on-board I/O devices, similar questions play out.</p>
<h2 id="working-out-maximum-delays">Working out maximum delays</h2>
<p>The figure I included above shows an opcode fetch cycle and I/O read/write cycles, but not a memory read or write cycle. As it turns out memory read cycles look almost the same as opcode fetch cycles with one key difference - the data lines are sampled on the falling edge of T3, not the rising edge. Taking a leaf from Application Note AN009602-0808 (“The Z180 Interfaced with the SCC at 10 MHz”) a simplified diagram showing a read and a write memory cycle will clear up the clutter nicely and show just what’s needed for memory timing constraints.</p>
<table>
<caption>Values for the timing parameters of the Z80L180-20. All times in ns.</caption>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: left;">No.</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">Label</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">Time</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">Purpose</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">6</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">t<sub>AD</sub></td>
<td style="text-align: left;">≤ 30</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">PHI rise to Address Valid Delay</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">7</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">t<sub>AS</sub></td>
<td style="text-align: left;">≥ 5</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Address Valid to /MREQ or /IORQ fall</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">8</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">t<sub>MED1</sub></td>
<td style="text-align: left;">≤ 25</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">PHI fall to /MREQ fall delay</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">9</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">t<sub>RDD1</sub></td>
<td style="text-align: left;">≤ 25</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">PHI fall to /RD fall delay</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">11</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">t<sub>AH</sub></td>
<td style="text-align: left;">≥ 5</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Address Hold time from /MREQ, /IORQ, /RD, /WR high</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">12</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">t<sub>MED2</sub></td>
<td style="text-align: left;">≤ 25</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">PHI fall to /MREQ rise delay</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">13</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">t<sub>RDD2</sub></td>
<td style="text-align: left;">≤ 25</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">PHI fall to /RD rise delay</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">15</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">t<sub>DRS</sub></td>
<td style="text-align: left;">≥ 10</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Data Read Set-up time</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">16</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">t<sub>DRH</sub></td>
<td style="text-align: left;">≥ 0</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Data Read Hold time</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">22</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">t<sub>WRD1</sub></td>
<td style="text-align: left;">≤ 25</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">PHI rise to /WR fall delay</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">23</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">t<sub>WDD</sub></td>
<td style="text-align: left;">≤ 25</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">PHI fall to Write Data Delay time</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">24</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">t<sub>WDS</sub></td>
<td style="text-align: left;">≥ 10</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Write Data Set-up time to /WR fall</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">25</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">t<sub>WRD2</sub></td>
<td style="text-align: left;">≤ 25</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">PHI fall to /WR rise delay</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">27</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">t<sub>WDH</sub></td>
<td style="text-align: left;">≥ 10</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Write Data Hold time from /WR rise</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<figure>
<img src="/images/z180-timing-memory.svg" alt="" /><figcaption>Memory access timing diagram, opcode fetch and write cycles.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>The only timing not specified in the table above is 1 (t<sub>CYC</sub>, the clock cycle time). I will use an 18.432MHz MEMS oscillator, the DSC1001DE5. This part is accurate to 10ppm, which means t<sub>CYC</sub> will fall between 54.253ns and 54.254ns, which I will call 54ns. It outputs 0.9xV<sub>DD</sub>, or 2.97V, with a rise and fall time no longer than 2ns. The duty cycle could be anywhere between 45% and 55%, or 24.3ns to 29.7ns.</p>
<p>A regular memory read cycle shortes the data window by only requiring that data has been set up t<sub>DRS</sub> before the falling edge of T3, rather than the rising edge. I/O read cycles are the same as regular memory read cycles, except that /IORQ replaces /MREQ and there is always at least one wait state. In Z80-compatible mode though, /IORQ and /RD fall after the rising edge of T2, so that’s a little trap to be wary of.</p>
<p>To read a byte from a typical memory chip, one will decode the address lines plus /MREQ to activate the chip enable input of the memory, then activate either output enable or write enable depending on whether /RD or /WR is active. /MREQ activates 5ns after the address lines have settled, or 25ns after T1 falls. T1 could fall as late as 29.7ns after T1 rises, so /MREQ will not become active until 54.7ns have elapsed. /RD will become active at the same time. This is 1.7ns after T2 has begun, leaving 53.3ns until T3 begins, and 43.3ns until the data must be available.</p>
<figure>
<img src="/images/z180-memory-read-timing.svg" alt="" /><figcaption>Laid out as a timeline, it’s starting to make sense.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>This 43.3ns is eaten up by address decoding to drive the SRAM’s /CE input, by any logic required to translate the CPU’s /RD and /WR outputs into the SRAM’s /OE and /WE inputs, by any buffering or logic level conversions required, and of course by the SRAM’s own timing constraints. Fortunately, these are easier to understand - in a nutshell, data will be ready at most 10ns after /CE is active and 6ns after /OE is active. The data outputs will be Hi-Z again 5ns after /OE goes high. These figures are specific to the SRAM chip I’m using: check your datasheet.</p>
<p>There’s also parasitics that add delay to the signal. On my sized board, this will be well below 3.3ns - the <a href="https://blog.zuken.com/how-to-calculate-trace-length-from-time-delay-value-for-high-speed-signals/">speed of signals</a> on stripline traces is close to 150mm/ns, so it’ll take less than one nanosecond for a signal to traverse my 10cm^2 board corner to corner. This leaves me a tidy 40ns to work with.</p>
<p>For SRAM, this is an enormous surplus of time, with a whopping 30ns available for logic. For Flash ROM, it’s not so much time. My chosen ROM is the SST39SF020A, a 2Mbit 55ns IC. 55ns is, of course, greater than 40ns. But all is not lost, because as with the SRAM the 55ns applies from the time /CE is active. Data will be available 35ns after /OE is active, so if I can decode the address lines and toggle /CE early enough I will have 5ns to activate /OE on the ROM and still have data available inside the zero wait state window. Data must be ready at t+98ns and the address lines are settled at t+30ns, leaving 10ns for address decoding and 3ns for parasitics.</p>
<p>The Z180 has a 16-bit I/O space so A16-A19 should all be low for any I/O request. Address decoding on ADDR alone can be fairly sure that if the ROM bits are set (A18, A19) that it’s really going to be a ROM request. In a similar vein, if A18 is set and A19 is clear it’s going to be an off-board memory request, and a wait state could be immediately generated, but I’m quite comfortable requiring software to manage this via the CPU’s wait state generator if off-board memory is needed.</p>
<figure>
<img src="/images/z180-memory-write-timing.svg" alt="" /><figcaption>My eyes are starting to glaze.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>When writing, the SRAM IC has from the fall of /WR to the fall of T3 to store data. /WR should fall no later than t+79ns, and T3 should fall no earlier than t+131.4ns. /WR will rise up to 25ns later. Timing constraint 26 (t<sub>WRP</sub>, write pulse width) guarantees that /WR will be low for at least 80ns. You could almost write the byte down on paper with that much time.</p>
<h2 id="wait-state-generation">Wait state generation</h2>
<p>Wait states are inserted between T2 and T3, either because the Z180’s internal wait state generator has been configure to insert them, or because the /WAIT signal is low when sampled at the fall of T2. The internal wait state generator can add zero to three wait states to every memory or I/O access, with three being added at reset.</p>
<p>The /WAIT signal must be asserted low at least t<sub>WS</sub> (15ns) before T2 falls, and held low at least t<sub>WH</sub> (10ns) after T2 falls. To allow the processor to continue, it must be de-asserted at least t<sub>WS</sub> before a TW clock cycle falls, and held high at least t<sub>WH</sub> after it falls.</p>
<p>T2 could fall as early as t+78.3ns, and /WAIT must be asserted low 15ns before that at t+63.3ns. If /WAIT is asserted in response to /MREQ falling at t+54.7ns then only 8.6ns is available. /WAIT transitions are ideally done on the rising edge of a system clock, but /MREQ might fall after T2 rises - if wait states are required for a memory read, they are likely to need to be generated either based on address alone or done using the internal wait state generator. For IO, there’s already one wait state inserted at a minimum, giving at least 62.6ns.</p>
<h2 id="interrupt-acknowledgement">Interrupt acknowledgement</h2>
<p>The Mode 0 and Mode 2 INT0 acknowledgement cycles both read a data byte from the bus, where only M1 and IORQ go low. In both cases there are two wait states, /M1 falls up to 35ns after T1 rises, /IORQ falls at least 125ns (2.5 clock cycles) after /M1 falls and at most 25ns after TW<sub>1</sub> falls. Data must be ready 10ns before T3 begins to rise. Assuming TW<sub>1</sub> falls late at 29.7ns and /IORQ falls 25ns after that, and a few ns for parasitics, there’ll be 40ns left in which to respond to the acknowledgement cycle with data on the bus.</p>
<p>Memory writes</p>
<ul>
<li>10 t<sub>M1D1</sub> PHI rise to M1 fall ≤ 35ns</li>
<li>28 t<sub>IOD1</sub> PHI rise/fall to IORQ fall ≤ 25ns</li>
<li>29 t<sub>IOD2</sub> PHI fall to IORQ rise ≤ 25ns</li>
<li>30 t<sub>IOD3</sub> M1 fall to IORQ fall ≥ 125ns</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="io-timing">IO timing</h2>
<p>IO read and write cycles differ from memory only by the addition of one mandatory wait cycle. This adds 54ns to all timing constraints. In the case of t<sub>WRP</sub>, the minimum write pulse time is 150ns.</p>
<h2 id="timing-constraint-summary">Timing constraint summary</h2>
<table>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Constraint</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">Description</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">Time</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Mem read</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">ADDR to data available</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">65ns</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Mem read</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">/MREQ, /RD fall to data available</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">40ns</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Mem write</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">/WR fall duration</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">80ns</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Mem wait</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">/MREQ fall to clock rise</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">-0.7ns</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>IO read</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">/IORQ, /RD fall to data available</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">94ns</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>IO write</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">/WR fall duration</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">150ns</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>IO wait</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">/IORQ fall to clock rise</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">50ns</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>INT0 read</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">/M1 and /IORQ fall to data available</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">40ns</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>The TRS-20 - boot up</title>
    <link href="https://bje.id.au/blog/posts/trs20/009-boot-it.html" />
    <id>https://bje.id.au/blog/posts/trs20/009-boot-it.html</id>
    <published>2020-02-19T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-02-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My 128 bytes each of ROM and RAM are working: the Z180 is executing my code.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>With my test rig re-wired using 22AWG wire (from a kit, I don’t have a nice stock of the stuff to trim to length myself yet) and looking neat, despite still only having eight address lines, I fired the thing up. Not pictured is a small extension that ties RESET high with a 10k resistor and adds a tactile switch to pull it low, as the Z180 doesn’t really behave properly without being reset.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://github.com/codebje/trs20-debug/blob/fe11a903a1df9553ae3c87e779e340607668d3f4/trs20.asm">code</a> that should be executed disables DRAM refresh, so my logic analyser images don’t have so much noise in them. After that, it just loops forever not doing anything.</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb1"><pre class="sourceCode z80asm"><code class="sourceCode z80asm"><span id="cb1-1"><a href="#cb1-1"></a><span class="fu">reset:</span>	<span class="dt">.org</span>	<span class="bn">$0000</span></span>
<span id="cb1-2"><a href="#cb1-2"></a>	ld	<span class="at">a</span>, <span class="bn">0</span></span>
<span id="cb1-3"><a href="#cb1-3"></a>	out0	(RCR), <span class="at">a</span>	<span class="co">; disable the DRAM refresh</span></span>
<span id="cb1-4"><a href="#cb1-4"></a>	jp	_start</span>
<span id="cb1-5"><a href="#cb1-5"></a></span>
<span id="cb1-6"><a href="#cb1-6"></a><span class="co">; … other RST vectors omitted …</span></span>
<span id="cb1-7"><a href="#cb1-7"></a></span>
<span id="cb1-8"><a href="#cb1-8"></a><span class="fu">_start:</span></span>
<span id="cb1-9"><a href="#cb1-9"></a>	nop</span>
<span id="cb1-10"><a href="#cb1-10"></a>	jp	_start</span></code></pre></div>
<p>After a reset, the data lines look like this. I’ve added handy little labels for the signals.</p>
<figure>
<img src="/images/boot-from-rom.png" alt="" /><figcaption>On reflection, it probably would have been easier to read as D7:0.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Decoding and cross-referencing these binary values with the listing file for the ROM image shows it executing exactly what it should, and it’s apparent that immediately after the <code class="sourceCode z80asm">out0</code> the DRAM refresh ceases, and the CPU repeatedly requests the <code class="sourceCode z80asm">nop</code> and <code class="sourceCode z80asm">jp</code> instructions</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>bits</th>
<th>hex</th>
<th>assembly</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><code>00111110</code></td>
<td><code>3E</code></td>
<td><code class="sourceCode z80asm">ld <span class="at">a</span>, <span class="bn">0</span></code></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><code>00000000</code></td>
<td><code>00</code></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><code>11101101</code></td>
<td><code>ED</code></td>
<td><code class="sourceCode z80asm">out0 (RCR), <span class="at">a</span></code></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><code>00111001</code></td>
<td><code>39</code></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><code>00110110</code></td>
<td><code>36</code></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><code>11000011</code></td>
<td><code>C3</code></td>
<td><code class="sourceCode z80asm">jp <span class="bn">$0038</span></code></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><code>00111000</code></td>
<td><code>38</code></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><code>00000000</code></td>
<td><code>00</code></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><code>00000000</code></td>
<td><code>00</code></td>
<td><code class="sourceCode z80asm">nop</code></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>I don’t think I’ve convinced friends or family that this is, in fact, quite an exciting milestone. Nevertheless, it is: I have written code that runs on my CPU. The rest of the computer is just details…</p>
<p>The STM32’s usefulness for this stage of the project is, I think, now at an end. It may return as a USB keyboard controller down the line, but this project is ready for PCB design.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, the PC104 headers I ordered arrived, after 84 days. My guess is they fell behind something in Customs and were only recently found. They were very well packed, and are undamaged, so I contacted the seller and placed another order that the seller didn’t ship. Since my refund didn’t include the tax I paid, and my new order did, I’ve now paid twice the tax on the headers, taking their total cost up to $12.70 for five 40-pin headers and two 64-pin headers. My stand-offs also arrived, so there’s now nothing in transit.</p>
<p>I also ordered and received an Altera MAX II CPLD minimal development board, for $11.56. This board saves me a lot of fiddly soldering making my own on perfboard, and will let me trial the use of a relatively cheap CPLD IC for address decoding or video output. I booted up Intel’s Quartus II to a sufficient level to verify the board works - to cut a long story short on it, it’s just a lot easier on a Mac to run Quartus in a desktop Linux VM than it is to try to make it work in Docker.</p>
<p>I’m going to mark the Debug section of the project as complete. It’s possible I’ll need further debugging aids later in the project, but each quarter I’ll want to review my targets and check they still make sense given what I’ve learned so far.</p>
<table style="width:86%;">
<caption>Project status update</caption>
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 21%" />
<col style="width: 8%" />
<col style="width: 10%" />
<col style="width: 13%" />
<col style="width: 10%" />
<col style="width: 11%" />
<col style="width: 11%" />
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: center;">Budget</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">CPU</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Power</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Keyboard</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Video</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Memory</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Debug</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">$233.61 of $400</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">██──</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">────</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">────</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">────</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">────</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">done</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>]]></summary>
</entry>

</feed>
